<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuation of the historie of France from the death of Charles the eight where Comines endeth, till the death of Henry the second. Collected by Thomas Danett Gentleman.</title>
            <author>Danett, Thomas, fl. 1566-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19807</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844898</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844898</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19807)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 493:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuation of the historie of France from the death of Charles the eight where Comines endeth, till the death of Henry the second. Collected by Thomas Danett Gentleman.</title>
                  <author>Danett, Thomas, fl. 1566-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 148 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas East for Thomas Charde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Intended as a continuation of the history of Philippe de Commynes, which Danett had translated.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Continuation of the Hiſtorie of</hi> France, from the death <hi>of Charles the eight where</hi> Comines endeth, till the death of Henry the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected</hi> By Thomas Danett Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON Printed by Thomas</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt for Thomas Charde. <hi>1600.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:2"/>
            <head>To the Right honorable my very good Lord <hi>the Lord Buckhurſt, Lord</hi> high Treaſorer of England and knight of the moſt <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order of the Garter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had Right Honorable about three yeares ſithence preſented to the late LORD TREASORER of worthie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie your Lordſhips prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor the Commentaries of <hi>Comines,</hi> tranſlated into our Engliſh tongue, I was earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſſed by ſome of my friends to continue the Hiſtorie of Fraunce, from Charles the eight where he endeth till this our preſent age, which a long time I vtterly refuſed to doe, knowing that to annex my poore collections to the workes of ſo excellent a writer as <hi>Comines</hi> is, ſhould be as arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant a part and as much to my diſcredit as if a
<pb facs="tcp:9751:3"/>
Painter ſhould haue attempted to finiſh the Image of Venus beegunne but not ended by Apelles, which was a worke of ſo rare excellencie that no Paynter after him durſt aduenture to perfect it. Notwithſtanding when I called to mynde that others before mee had attempted this that they required at my hands, and withall not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to withſtand the importunitie of my friendes I beganne though ſomewhat timorouſly to take penne in hand. And whereas there are in all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings two kindes of methodes, the one procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the cauſes to the effectes, and the other iudging of the cauſes by the effectes which is called <hi>Iudicium a poſteriori:</hi> my ſelfe not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to performe the former as Comines doth, who was priuie to the hidden miſteries, of Princes deſeignes, and of Counſell with their ſecret cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: determined onely to follow the ſecond courſe, namely to ſet downe the effectes and the naked truth forbearing either to giue graue aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſments as well to Princes themſelues as to their ſeruaunts as hee doth, or to enter into deepe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of high points of pollicie &amp; gouernment (as a matter farre aboue my capacitie) wherewith his workes are ſingularly beautified. In the which courſe hauing waded in the Hiſtorie of Fraunce till the death of Henry the ſecond and purpoſing to continew it further, both my hart &amp; hand fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and my pen fell foorth of my fingers of it owne accord.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9751:3"/>
For the actions of the ciuill warres of Fraunce are ſo blouddie, cruell, and barbarous and ſo farre I will not ſay ſrom all Chriſtianitie, but from all humanitie and militarie diſcipline vſed in former times, that for my owne part I iudge them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to bee buried in the dongeon of eternall obliuion. Agreeable to the which actions were alſo the effects wherof my ſelfe haue beene an eie witneſſe. For paſſing out of Spaine through France in the yeare 77, in companie of a Gentleman of good ſeruice not long ſithens gone to God, whom hir Maieſtie employed at that time to the King of Spaine for hir affaires: we found ſuch a wildernes in all the country betwene <hi>Bayonne</hi> and <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> that whole forreſts and woods were turned vp and conſumed, the townes vtterly deſolated, the people deſpearſed, the churches quite ſubuerted, and the children (a lamentable thing to bee recorded) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining vnchriſtened by the ſpace of ten yeares, which bred in mee ſuch a commiſeration, to ſee ſo noble a member of Chriſtendome ſo miſerablye torne in peeces with hir owne teeth, that it did not onelie viſiblie as it were ſet before mine eyes the deſtruction of Sodoma &amp; Gomorha, and the rude Chaos wherein the world lay buried and hidden, before God placed all things in this goodly order which wee now ſee them in: but alſo made mee call to minde the example of <hi>Africanus Minor,</hi> who wept bitterly with a certaine <hi>Sinpathie</hi> of ſorrow, whan he ſaw <hi>Carthage</hi> all on flaming fier, calling to
<pb facs="tcp:9751:4"/>
minde that the like mought happen to his owne countrey Rome in time to come. The vices that ouerflowed Fraunce at the beeginning of their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile warres are noted to bee theſe three, <hi>Magia, Atheiſmus, Libido,</hi> which I pray God England bee free from at this day. But I will no longer dwell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this argument, leaſt my Epiſtle become to your honourable Lordſhip odious, and my booke bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in it ſelfe monſtrous by hauing to great a head to ſo ſmall a bodie, wherfore to returne to my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall purpoſe, hauing reduced the Hiſtorie of Fraunce, ſo farre as for the reaſons aboue aledged I determined to proceede in it, I was ſoone reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to whom to dedicate theſe my ſimple labours, for hauing preſented <hi>Comines</hi> to your Lordſhips predeceſſor, to whom could I fitlier conſecrate this my continuaunce of his Hiſtorie then to your Lordſhip, being his ſucceſſor in office, in honour, in gouernment, in Wiſedome, and in all other vertues beelonging to a moſt worthie counſellour ſo that GOD hath rayſed you vp vnder hir moſt excellent Maieſtie, to bee no leſſe famous in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Councell then others are in matters of warre, which <hi>Cicero</hi> as your Lordſhip knowerh preſerreth farre beefore warly actions, beecauſe Councell preſerueth the common welth without warrs, but warre cannot deſend it without coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. The handeling of the worke is meane I confeſſe, and too<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnworthie of ſo noble a patron: yet notwithſtanding it contayneth the principall
<pb facs="tcp:9751:4"/>
matters of ſtate that paſſed in th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe parts by the ſpace of three ſcore yeares. Wherefore if your Lordſhip ſhall vouchſafe to accept it as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in the Scripture dyd the poore Widowes Mite: I ſhall thincke my ſelfe a happie man in hauing obtained the fruit of my deſier, and ſhall daylie pray to Almightie GOD long to preſerue your Lordſhip in all honor and felicitie, as well for the aduauncement of hir Maieſties ſeruice, as for the benefit of the whole common wealth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips<lb/>
moſt humble and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to commaund<lb/>
                  <hi>Thomas Dannett.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:5"/>
            <list>
               <item>In the Epiſtle in the firſt line laſt page for thoſe read theſe.</item>
               <item>Page. 29. line. 18. for Nauara reade Nouara.</item>
               <item>Page 34. line 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in battaile, read in a battaile.</item>
               <item>Page 46. line 12. for eſtate, read eſtates.</item>
               <item>Page 69. line 12. for charge, read great charge.</item>
               <item>Page 81. line 7. for predeceſſors, read predeceſſor.</item>
               <item>Page 87. line. 8. for vs, read vp.</item>
               <item>Page. 94. line 23. for Roſſam, reade Roſseim.</item>
               <item>Page 102. line 15. for Aughien, read Anghien.</item>
               <item>Page 121 line. 2. for duchie, read ducheſſe.</item>
               <item>Page 139. line. 21. for 20000. read 10000.</item>
               <item>For Aluiana reade in all places Aluiane.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9751:5"/>
            <head>A Continuation of the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of Fraunce, from the death</hi> of Charles the eight where Comines endeth till the death of Henry <hi>the ſecond, namely till the yeere</hi> 1559.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>LEVVIS the twelfth of that name King of FRAVNCE.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Lewis the twelfth commeth to the crowne, hee is deuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from his wife, and marrieth the Lady Anne, King Charles his widow and heire of Bretaine, A briefe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the euills that enſewed that marriage.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the death of King Charles <note place="margin">1498.</note> the eight, Lewis Duke of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans as next male of the blood royall ſucceded to the crowne of Fraunce by the name of Lewis the twelfth, a Prince as well beefore as after his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the crowne ſubiect to great varietie of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. The firſt thing hee attempted after he had ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9751:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his eſtate, was to bee deuorced from his wife the Lady Iane daughter to King Lewis the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, pretending that hee had maried hir by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, &amp; neuer had any carnall knowledge of hir. But becauſe hee doubted how his Realme would digeſt, ſo great an iniurie offered to this Lady, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Kings daughter and ſiſter &amp; a moſt vertuous Princeſſe, who had alſo beene his wife a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of yeares, and had by exceſſiue ſute and manie teares begged his life of king Charles hir brother, after the wars of Bretaine ended, wherein the ſaide Duke of Orleans (as before you haue heard) was taken priſoner: hee ſought to the Pope for reliefe, hoping vnder coulour of religion to cloake his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly purpoſe, and to iuſtifie by authoritie of the Church his ambitious deſire, to ioyne himſelfe in marriage with Anne widdow of the late King Charles and heire of Bretaine, thereby to hold ſtill the ſaid Dutchie of Bretaine vnited to the crowne of Fraunce, which otherwiſe muſt haue beene ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from it, if this Lady had beene beſtowed els where. Alexander the ſeuenth ſo often mentioned in the warrs of Charles the eight, a ſpaniard borne of the houſe of Borgia continewed ſtill Pope at this time, a man apt to imbrace any wicked motion that mought tend either to the filling of his cofers, or to the aduancement of his houſe. This Pope had a ſonne named <hi>Valentinus Borgia,</hi> (a ſinke of all fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe) the ſelfe ſame that had beene hoſtage with king charles in his Italian warrs being at that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9751:6"/>
time a Church man and named Cardinall of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: &amp; had eſcaped from him as in the ſaid warres of Italy mention is already made. This Borgia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing lately renounced his Cardinals hatt, had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken himſelfe to the warres, &amp; was entred into the Kings pay. And his father exchaunging ſpirituall graces for temporall poſſeſſions, was contented to graunt the king a Bull of deuorce from the ſaid La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Iane his wiſe with theſe conditions, that his ſaid ſonne Borgia mought be made Duke of Valence a Citie in Daulphine, haue the charge of a company of men of armes vnder the king, marry with Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotte daughter of <hi>Monſieur d'Alebret</hi> a great Prince in Guyenne, &amp; receaue a yearely penſion of 20000. crownes and as much reuenew of inheritance, all the which conditions were yelded vnto, &amp; by that meanes the Bull of deuorce obtained, and the King married the ſaid Queene Anne heire of Bretaine. I <note place="margin">1499.</note> know not well who is moſt to be cried out of in this caſe, either the Pope for graunting ſo wicked a Bull, or the king for his extreme ambition and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude towards his wife, or his people for ſoothing him vp &amp; encouraging him to ſo deteſtable a fact, or the Queene Dowager hir ſelf in accepting ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly a marriage, eſpecially conſidering that ſhe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing been married before to a king of France whom ſhee could not enioy but by diſmiſſion of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wife to giue hir place: and beeing puniſhed therefore as well by the ſodaine death of the ſayde king hir huſband, as by the loſſe of all hir children
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9751:7"/>
begotten in that vnlawfull marriage: durſt now not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding aduenture vpon a ſecond huſband after the ſame ſort. But ſure it well appeared that God was much offended with this match, for if we conſider firſt the Popes end &amp; his ſonnes, the one of the which poiſoned himſelfe with a flaggon of wine, which his ſaid ſonne and he had prepared for the poiſoning of certaine Cardinals their enemies, and the other after al his great conqueſts in Italie, &amp; his fauours in Fraunce, was ſodainely ſpoyled of all that he held in both thoſe Countries, ſent priſoner into Spaine, and laſtly ſlaine being a miſerable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond in the Realme of Nauarra: Secondarely if we behold the miſeries that fell vpon the king, and the great diſhonors and loſſes he receaued euen till the time of his death, being toſſed and chaſed like a tennis ball, firſt cleane out of Italy by a prince in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer much inferiour to himſelfe, and afterwards al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cleane out of his owne Realme by a confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie of moſt of the Princes and ſtates of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt him in the laſt periode of his age: Thirdly if we waie with our ſelues the continuall troubles the realme of Fraunce hath endured euer ſince this wicked marriage, vnder the gouernment of this Ladies of-ſpring euen till this very day. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if wee obſerue how in this our age hir diſcent is vtterly diſpoſſeſſed of hir Dutchie of Bretayne (which was the onely occaſion of this vngodly match) and the ſaid Dutchie fallen to the hands of a king a meere ſtranger to hir &amp; none of hir line: we
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9751:7"/>
muſt of neceſſitie confeſſe that God is a iuſt iudge, and puniſheth ſharplie ſuch offences, howſoeuer flatterers that are about Princes ſooth them vp and encourage them to ſuch wicked acts cleane forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God and his commaundements, if the breach thereof may further their affaires or enlarge their dominions. Examples heerof are plentifull both in ſacred and prophane Hiſtories, ſo that it were but loſt labour to ſpend much breath in this diſcourſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>The king conquereth the Dutchie of Milan, Lodouic Sforce recouereth it, and preſently after loſeth it againe, and both hee and his brother Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Aſcanius are caried priſoners into France.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His matter of deuorce hauing ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded according to the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, hee made peace with all his neighbours rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about him, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Ferdinande</hi> King of <hi>Aragon, Maximilian</hi> King of <hi>Romaines</hi> and <hi>Archduc Philip</hi> his ſonne, and with <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> which beeing done hee preſently leuied men, and made friends on all ſides, purpoſing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade the Dutchie of Milan, held ſtill as yet by Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douic Sforce ſurnamed the Moore, the ſelfe ſame that called King Charles the eight into Italie as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue heard: which alſo the King ſoone conquered, for you ſhall vnderſtand that the ſaide
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9751:8"/>
Lodouic was hated of his owne people, as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his great tirannie, as alſo for poyſoning his Nephew right heire of Milan, at the leaſt heire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. Farther hee was fallen out with his beſt friends y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Venetians about Piſa, who alſo partly for extreame hatred that they bare againſt him: and partly for greedineſſe of Cremona &amp; the countrey of Guyradadda, which the king promiſed them for their part of the victorie: dyd not onely incourage the king to paſſe into Italie and inuade Milan, but entered alſo into league with him, ſo that the ſaide Lodouic was deſtitute of all help, the Pope and the Venetians beeing in league with the King, and the poore King of Naples Frederic vnable to defend his owne, much leſſe to giue Lodouic any ayde. So that after the French armie had taken <hi>La Roccad'Arazza, Anon, Valentia, Baſignane, voghera, Chaſteauneuf, Pontcorona,</hi> and <hi>Tortona:</hi> and that Galeas of Saint <hi>Seuerin</hi> to his great reproch, had through cowardiſe abandoned <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Dertona,</hi> and that <hi>Pauia</hi> had of their owne accord receiued the French, the Venetians alſo inuading the ſaid <hi>Dutchie</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> on the other ſide: the ſaid Lodouic aſtoniſhed with the loſſe of ſo manie townes, miſtruſting his owne people, and beeing abandoned of all his friends &amp; principall ſeruants: fled with his children and a great maſſe of monie to the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> into <hi>Germanie,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after whoſe departure the Citie of Milan yeelded to the French, the Caſtle being alſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9751:8"/>
vnto them by the treaſon of <hi>Bernardin de Corte</hi> Captaine thereof. Soone after the whole ſtate of Genoua ſubmitted it ſelfe likewiſe to the King, and Cremona with the Countrey of Guyradadda were deliuered to the Venetians according to the Kings promiſe. In eight daies Lodouic loſt this ritch and noble Dutchie, ſo ſmall aſſurance is in worldly honors. The king hauing ſetled the ſtate of Milan, &amp; abated y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exceſſiue exactions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they paide in Lodouics time, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great though not to the full contentment of the people, for they looked to haue had all paiments cleane aboliſhed and taken away, and hauing giuen forces to the Duke of Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noys for the recouerie of thoſe townes in Romania that appertained to the Church: returned to Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where hee was welcommed with new ioyes beecauſe of the birth of his Daughter Claude. But <note place="margin">1500</note> this his good ſucceſſe was ſoone altered, for the <hi>Milanois</hi> beeing by nature variable and inconſtant, and alſo miſliking the rough gouernement of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iames of Treuoul, whom the king had left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him for his Lieutenant, who beeing of the Guelph faction, vſed to rudely thoſe of the faction Guibeline: and farther the people not beeing able to endure the inſolencies of the French ſouldiours: ſecretly ſolicited Lodouic to returne, who not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this opportunitie, but leuying with ſpeed 12000 Swyſſers, by the fauour of the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> but with his owne money, and 8000. Italians, entered into the Dutchie of Milan with all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9751:9"/>
diligence, and as ſodainely recouered the whole countrey as beefore hee had loſt it, all ſaue the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Milan with ſome other few places, and the ſtate of Genoua which held ſtill for the king, ſuch mutabilitie is not onely in the people of this eſtate, but in all the vulgare ſort throughout Italie. Bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this <hi>d'Aubigny</hi> and Treuoul Gouernours of the French in the ſayde Duchie were at great variance, which vtterly ſubuerted the kings afflicted affaires, in ſuch ſort that hee was forced to remoue them both and to commit the gouernement of the armie to Trimouille, who by his wiſdome hauing reconciled them together, ioyned them in equall authoritie with himſelfe, ſo that the armie for two gouernours had three. But the king beeing excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly moued with this ſodaine loſſe of the Duchie of Milan leuyed 600 Launces and a great armie of Swyſſers and ſent them with all diligence to Milan, which Lodouic vnderſtanding retired to Nouara, where the French armie beeſieged him. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he were in ſtate to fight with his enemies and ment alſo ſo to doe: yet the Swyſſers that ſerued him beeing corrupted with French crownes by meanes of the Swyſſers Captaines that were in the French Campe, refuſed to fight againſt their countrey men and kinſmen, wherewith Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douic beeing in vtter deſpaire, and doubting to bee deliuered by them into his enemies hands, with great difficultie obtained of them that hee might march among them as a common Swyſſer ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9751:9"/>
till hee ſhould bee conueyed to ſome place of ſaftie. But the matter beeing diſcouered to Trimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uille, whoſe mony made euery thing knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: he was apprehended as he marched like a common ſouldier among them, &amp; preſently ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce, where hee remayned priſoner in the tower of Loches till his death, not once being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings preſence nor ſpeech. And ſo this Prince whoſe ambitious deſires cauſed him, firſt to poiſon his Nephew, and then to ſet all Italie on fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by calling in the French, and likewiſe to depart from his league with the Venetians (being his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaftie) for greedines of hauing the towne of Piſa, which he ſought to draw out of their ſubiection to his obedience, and laſtly who neuer held faith nor promiſe with any man longer then it ſerued for his owne profit, was now abandoned of all men, and betrayed by thoſe whom hee had brought into I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly for his principall ſuccour and defence, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his daies in a miſerable dongeon, where all his extrauagant thoughts were cloaſed vp within the compaſſe of a narrow rome, his brother the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Aſcanius,</hi> found meanes to conueigh his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers children ſafe into Germany, but was himſelfe ſoone after his brother taken priſoner by the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and ſent likewiſe by the Kings commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (though not without great diſhonor to the Venetian eſtate) into Fraunce, where he was vſed with much more fauour and liberty than his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was (for he had the whole Realme of Fraunce
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9751:10"/>
for his priſon) and in the end by the meanes or rather through the ſimplicitie of the Cardinall of Amboyſe returned againe into Italie, where hee was reſtored to his former eſtate and dignitie. And thus the King ſoone recouered the Dutchie of Milan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>By a confederacie betweene the kings of Fraunce and Spaine, Frederick King of Naples loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his realme. The two Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>part it bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, the King of Spaine in the end obtaineth the whole, Pope Alexauder dyeth Iulius the ſecond ſuccedeth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT this Ptinces minde not beeing ſatisfied with one good <note place="margin">1501.</note> ſucceſſe, but the more hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the more his ambition being inflamed, he determined to attempt the conqueſt of the Realme of NAPLES not long beefore reuolted from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor, as in KING CHARLES his warrs of Italy ample mention is already made.</p>
                  <p>And to the end hee mought obtayne the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9751:10"/>
without any reſiſtaunce, hee determined to make the KING of SPAINE partaker with him of the bootie, leaſt hee beeing a neighbour in the Ile of SICILE to the Realme of NAPLES and a kinſeman to the King thereof, and hauing alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alreadie entered into the Countrey for the ſayde Kings defence: ſhould hinder his conqueſt of the ſaide Realme.</p>
                  <p>This offer was ſoone embraced by the KING of SPAINE, who beeing receyued into the ſtrong places of the ſaide Realme of NAPLES, vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of defending them for KING FREDERIC, detayned them for him ſelfe and vtterlie ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſayde FREDERIC, notwithſtanding both the truſt that hee had repoſed in the KING of SPAINE, and the neere kindred that was bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them.</p>
                  <p>Thus FREDERIC beeing at one inſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded by the FRENCH and beetrayed by the SPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIARD, yeelded his Realme in deſpite of the ſayde KING of SPAINE into the handes of KING LEVVIS, and went with him into FRAVNCE, where hee liued in verye honourable eſtate till his death.</p>
                  <p>But his ſonne Ferdinand Duke of Calabria, whome Conſalue the king of Spaines generall in the ſaide Realme of Naples, had giuen his oath to ſet at libertie, ſo ſoone as he ſhould bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into his hands: was notwithſtanding the ſayd oath ſent into Spayne to the king of ARAGON,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9751:11"/>
where (after manie yeeres impriſonment) hee marryed in the yeare 1522. with the LADIE GERMANE of FOIX, widdow of the ſaide KING of ARAGON, a rich LADIE but barrayne, which marriage was made by the EMPEROVR CHARLES, who greatly fauoured the ſaide Duke of Calabria, becauſe hee had refuſed to be taken out of <hi>La Roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Sciatiua,</hi> which was the priſon wherin he lay, and to bee made head of a rebellion that happened in Spaine called <hi>La Santa giunta</hi> whereof heereafter mention ſhall bee made. This <hi>Ferdinand</hi> Duke of Calabria was the laſt of the race of the firſt <hi>Alfonſe</hi> King of Naples, for two of his bretheren died be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, one in Italy the other in Fraunce. But to returne to the Hiſtory, the treaſon of the King of Spaine towardes King <hi>Frederic</hi> was no greater in this action, than the error of the king of Fraunce, as the ſequele well delared. For whereas the ſaide <hi>Frederic</hi> offered King Lewis to hold the Realme of Naples of him, and to pay him for it yeere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great tribute, by meanes whereof no man ſhould haue commaunded in the ſaide Realme but his tributarie king (who alwaies muſt haue depended vpon him) and himſelfe: he now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a neighbour PRINCE, though not ſo mightie yet much more ſubtill than himſelfe, and deuided the kingdome with him beeing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned by his owne money and his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes blood, and ſoone after loſt the whole to his owne great diſhonor and damage.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:9751:11"/>
For you ſhall vnderſtand that the very next yeere after the partition made of the ſayde Realme bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <note place="margin">1502.</note> theſe two Princes, they fell at varience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the bounds of their territories, and beecauſe the French were at that inſtant the ſtronger, they tooke many places in the Countrey called the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitanat (which was the prouince in controuerſie beetweene them) from the Spaniards. But the next yeere after the Spaniards haueing renforced their companies not onely recouered all their loſſes, but alſo wanne diuers places fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the French, &amp; namely <note place="margin">1503.</note> RVBOS a towne not far from BARLETTA, where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they tooke priſoner <hi>Monſieur de la Paliſſe.</hi> And notwithſtanding that by the entermiſe of <hi>Archduc Philip</hi> ſonne in law to the king of Spaine (who this yeere came into Fraunce) a peace was concluded betweene the kings of Fraunce and Spaine, vpon the ſecuritie whereof king Lewis wholy repoſing himſelfe, forbare to ſend new ſupplies to NAPLES: yet the king of Spaine very cunningly delayed the confirmation of the ſayde peace beecauſe hee ſaw his affaires to proſper well in Italie through the French kings ouergreat credulitie and negligence, and in the end flatly diſauowed al his ſonne in laws actions. And Conſalue his Generall in the ſayde Realme of NAPLES notwithſtanding the Archducs commaundements often ſent vnto him to ſurceaſe all Hoſtilitie in thoſe parts: not onely refuſed ſo to doe becauſe hee receiued noe ſuch commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement from his Maſter, but alſo proceeded ſtill in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9751:12"/>
his conqueſts, and wanne from the French diuers townes, defeated the Duke of ATRY who led cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine French bandes and tooke him priſoner, and afterward alſo ouerthrew Monſieur <hi>d'Aubigny</hi> and tooke him priſoner, and laſtlie at the battayle of Cirignolles vanquiſhed the whole power of france, and ſlew in the fielde with diuers noble men the braue Duke of NEMOVRS generall of the French forces.</p>
                  <p>Farther the ſayde Conſalue vſing the benefit of this victorie marched preſently before Naples, and without reſiſtance entered into the towne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it to the obedience of the King of Spaine, and ſoone after tooke alſo the Caſtles, and conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red almoſt the whole Realme. In the meane time dyed Pope ALEXANDER the ſixt, and PIVS the third was choſen Pope, who dying alſo at the ende of ſixe and twentie dayes, the Cardinall <hi>Petri ad Vincula</hi> (ſo often mentioned in the warrs of Charles the eight) ſucceeded by the name of IVLIVS the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>The King in the meane time made great preparation to recouer his Realme of NAPLES ſo ſhamefully and diſhonorably loſt, and entered as farre as the Riuer GARILLIANO called LIRIS in auncient times, where diuers attempts were made by the French to paſſe the ſayde Riuer, which all were ouerthrowen and brought to nought by the wiſdome and induſtrie of Conſalue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9751:12"/>
In the ende, what through want of victualls and lack of money which the kings officers moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie detayned from them, by meanes alſo where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the companies that the King payed were not halfe compleat: what through foule weather and what through the induſtrie and diligence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalue who tooke aduauntage of all theſe their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders: the French were forced to abandon their fortes vppon the ſayde Riuer, and to retire to CAIETTA which they yet held, whether not onely the ſayde inconueniences accompanied them, but alſo Conſalue with all ſpeede purſued them and there beeſieged them.</p>
                  <p>But they not beeing able to defend the towne <note place="margin">1504</note> yeelded it by compoſition and retourned into Fraunce, and thus Conſalue obtayned the Realme of NAPLES without bloudſhed, and had euer after the Title of great Captaine, beecauſe of his noble exployts giuen vnto him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:9751:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Frederic King of Naples and Elizabeth Queene of Spaine both dye, by a mariage beetweene the King of Aragon and the Lady Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Foix, peace is made beetweene Fraunce and Spaine. Archduc Philip dyeth. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia is reſtored to the pope, Genoua rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and is ſoone reduced to the Kings obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this yeere dyed FREDERIC king of Naples, and likewiſe ELIZABETH <note place="margin">1504.</note> Queene of Caſtile wife to king Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand, whoſe death cauſed the ſaid king Ferdinand the rather to deſire peace with Fraunce, becauſe hee doubted that the gouernment of Caſtile (notwithſtanding his wiues teſtament whereby hee was appointed Gouernour thereof during his life) ſhould bee taken from him, and deliuered to <hi>Archduc Philip</hi> his ſonne in law, whoſe wife was heyre thereof.</p>
                  <p>The yeere 1505 was a yeere ſubiect to great Famine and Peſtilence, and in this yeere a ſecret <note place="margin">1505.</note> conſederacie beetweene the greateſt Princes in Chriſtendome againſt the Venetians beegan co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly to bee treated of, which afterwards alſo tooke effect. And the better to bring that matter to paſſe, by practiſe of the Pope who was a deadly enemy to the Venetians, as was alſo the King of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9751:13"/>
Fraunce, becauſe for want of their help he loſt the Realme of Naples as hee ſaide: peace was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded betweene Fraunce and Spaine, the French king enclining therevnto, to the end hee mought haue his reuenge of the ſaid venetians, &amp; the ſpaniard by that meanes to haue a rampar againſt his ſon in law the Archduc Philip, wherfore in conſideration of a marriage betweene the ſaid King of Spaine and the Lady Germaine of Foix ſiſters daughter to the king of Fraunce, the ſaide King yelded vp to the king of Spaine all his title &amp; intereſt to the Realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, by the which meanes theſe two Princes that ſo long had continued in deadly warrs, concluded peace and became friends &amp; allies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the king of Spaine heereby alſo fortified himſelfe mightely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſonne in law the Archduc Philip who in the beginning of the yeere 1506 ſailed into Spaine <note place="margin">1506.</note> with a purpoſe to take the gouernment of Caſtile in to his owne hands. But by the entermiſe of the NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the realme, an accord was made betweene his father in law &amp; him, and the king of Aragon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted into his realme of Naples with very hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable conditions. But not long after died the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc, &amp; becauſe his wife daughter of the ſaid King Ferdinand was diſtracted of hir wits, both hir ſelfe (being mad in all points but in this) &amp; likewiſe hir whole realme of Caſtile reuoqued king Ferdinand out of Italy &amp; reeſtabliſhed him in the gouernment of Caſtile, till ſuch time as Charles the ſaide Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducs ſonne &amp; nephew of the ſaid Ferdinand being
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9751:14"/>
very yong ſhould be of age to gouerne the Realme him ſelfe. About this tyme alſo the Pope by ayde of the French king, recouered <hi>Bolonia</hi> from the <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuoli</hi> though litle to the kings honor who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſayd citie of <hi>Bolonia,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Bentiuoli</hi> into his protection in the yeare 1500, &amp; yet now betrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Pope, more regarding the Popes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne honour and faith, for the which fact y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope wel requited him as hereafter you ſhall heare. But to returne to the french affaires. The <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuoys</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1507.</note> ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings greatnes ſo mightely to decline in Italie by loſſe of the realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> and being alſo deſirous to recouer their libertie; determined to rebell, and to withdraw their obedience fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, which alſo they did, and began firſt to chace away his officers, &amp; afterwards to ſpoile the noble mens houſes in the towne. But the king being aduertiſed thereof, paſſed in perſon with a mightie armie into Italie, &amp; ſoone reduced them to their former obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which being done he preſently diſmiſſed his army and returned into France, therby deliuering all the ſtates of Italie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ielouſie they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of him, that he ment to make ſome farther attempt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>A confederacie is made at Cambray againſt the venetians, the french ouerthrow them at the battell of Guyradadda.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SOone after this, the practiſe aboue mentioned <note place="margin">1508.</note> againſt the Venetians, which had been long trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted off vnder hand, &amp; had long ere this ben conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9751:14"/>
but that ſo many ſtrings could not ſo ſoone be tuned (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope &amp; the kings of Romains, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; Aragon were concurring in the accion): brake openly foorth. For you ſhall vnderſtand that Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> hating the Venetians extremly, becauſe they detained from him certain towns in <hi>Romania</hi> belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to the Church, &amp; receiued into their protection the church rebells, namely, the <hi>Bentiuoli</hi> &amp; others: laboured to make peace among theſe Princes, and to conuert their armes not againſt the Infidels but againſt the ſaid Venetians, which alſo he effected in the end, the rather becauſe euery one of theſe Princes had priuate quarells to them.</p>
                  <p>The Popes quarell you haue already heard, and the cauſe of the french kings diſpleaſure towards them I haue in part touched alſo before, &amp; ſaid it was for that they refuſed to ayde him in his wars of Naples according to their league, which was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely loſſe of the ſaid realme as he ſaid. But in very deede his principall hatred againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was becauſe they held <hi>Cremona</hi> &amp; the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie of <hi>Guiradadda</hi> members of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Duchie</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> which notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wer deliuered to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his own agreeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, at ſuch time as they aided him to chace <hi>Lodouic Sforce</hi> out of the ſaid duchie: yet now conſidering their ingratitude towards him, &amp; withall how neceſſary thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries were for the ſtrength &amp; defence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Milan: he determined to recouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe into his owne hands. <hi>Maximilian</hi> and the <hi>Archduc Charles</hi> his Nephew had an auncient quarell to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, firſt for <hi>Verona, Padoua, vinc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſe</hi> and diuers other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9751:15"/>
townes with helde from the Empire, and ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relie for the countries of <hi>Friull</hi> and <hi>Treuiſa,</hi> which they with hold from the houſe of Auſtria.</p>
                  <p>Beſides that Maximillians quarrell was lately great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie increaſed, for euen in this very yeere 1508, they had not onely denied him paſſage through their countries for his ſouldiers, whoſe paſſage he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be onely becauſe he ment to goe to take the crowne imperiall at Rome, though they knew well the contrarie: but had alſo defeated his companies being entred into their dominions by force. And notwithſtanding that they had reaſon ſo to doe knowing his purpoſe to be no thing leſſe then that which he pretended, &amp; that he came with a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſurpriſe thoſe places which he claimed to be his: yet this defeate of his men exaſperated him not a little againſt them, for few Princes can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the contrarying of their wills be it neuer ſo iuſtly done.</p>
                  <p>The king of Spaine likewiſe hated them becauſe they held in the realme of Naples certaine townes engaged to them by Ferdinand King of Naples in the warrs of Charles the eight, which by no meanes they would reſtore.</p>
                  <p>Thus all theſe princes beeing animated againſt them, a generalleague was concluded among them againſt the ſaid Venetians at Cambray. The Pope <note place="margin">1509.</note> began firſt with ſpirituall armes, and ſent forth a terrible bull againſt them, from the which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the next generall Counſell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9751:15"/>
But of all the other Princes the king of Fraunce was firſt in a redineſſe and with an armie of 24000 men inuaded their dominions. And they encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered him with noe leſſe forces, and vnder the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Aluiane &amp; the Earle of Petillian gaue him battaile, in the which they were ouerthrowen, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillian ſayde through Aluianas temeritie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uergreat heate, and Aluiana ſayde through Petilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans cowardiſe or malice, who would not ayde him with his troups beecauſe the battaile was fought againſt his aduice.</p>
                  <p>But howſoeuer it were, certaine it is that the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians loſt in this battayle 10000 men, and Alui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana himſelfe was taken priſoner therein. This bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel is called the battell of Guiradadda or <hi>de la Vaile.</hi> After this victorie almoſt all the townes that the Venetians held in Italie, yeelded to the king, who reſtored to the king of Romaines thoſe that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Title to, &amp; to the Pope thoſe that hee quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eled, which being done he returned to Milan. This yeare dyed Henry king of England the two and twenteth of Aprill to whom ſucceeded Henry his ſonne, a young Prince eighteene yeares of age, of whom heereafter ample mencion ſhall bee made, and this yeare alſo the ſeuenteenth of October dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Philip de Commines</hi> Lord of Argenton, a worthie counſeler and no leſſe worthie writer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9751:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>The Venetians are reconciled to the Pope and the King of Aragon, all they three toyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the King. The Swyſſers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beecome the Kings enemies, the quarell beetweene the Pope and the Duke of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, the Pope loſeth Bolonia. The King withdraweth himſelfe from the Popes obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. The Pope excommunicateth the whole Realme of Fraunce. The battayle of Rauenna wherein the Pope and his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federats are ouerthrowen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Venetians beeing thus low brought and ſeeing ſo many princes againſt them, determined to take ſome courſe to diſſolue this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, wherfore they humbled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues firſt vnto the Pope, and found meanes to be reconciled vnto him, for you ſhal vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that after this victorie aboue mentioned, partly commiſeration of the venetians moued him to fauour them, but eſpecially the kings greatneſſe in Italie beecame very odious &amp; terrible vnto him, in ſuch ſort that he alſo ſecretly withdrew the king of Aragon from the kings friendſhip, &amp; ioyned him in league with the Venetians: they reſtoring vnto him the ports in Pouille aboue mencioned which they held: and the Pope himſelfe putting him into a continuall ielouſie that if the french affaires proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9751:16"/>
in Italie, he ſhould bee conſtrained againe to fight for the realme of Naples, notwithſtanding his mariage with the kings niece. But in very truth the thing that moſt troubled the Pope, &amp; moſt cauſed him to enuie the kings good ſucceſſe, was ielouſie of his owne eſtate, beecauſe many cardinalls hated him, and obiected many crimes againſt him, all the which had intelligence with the king, wherfore the ſaide Pope to the ende hee mought omit no thing that tended to the ouerthrow of the kings procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings &amp; theſe Cardinalls practiſes, hiered the Swyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers <note place="margin">1510.</note> to inuade the Duchie of Milan and to abandon their league with the french, which being begun by Lewis the xi. expired at this very inſtant, &amp; could not be renewed, beecauſe the Swyſſers demanded proudly greater pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had before, which the king partly through diſdaine &amp; partly through couetouſneſſe would not condeſcend vnto, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they entered into league with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope againſt the king, &amp; inuaded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dutchie of Milan, but for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of victuals &amp; monie they were forced at this time to returne home, without any exploit done. Farther the ſaid Pope now ſhewing himſelfe openly to bee the kings enemy, together with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Venetians prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a nauie to ſurpriſe <hi>Genoua,</hi> and ſo this Pope that was the firſt kindler of this warre againſt the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, &amp; the principall author of the league of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray:</hi> was alſo himſelfe the firſt that brake it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the kindeneſſe that hee had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the kings hands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:9751:17"/>
But the nauie aboue mentioned appoynted to inuade Genoua was ouerthrowen and diſperſed by the French nauie, and ſo all the Popes enterpriſes againſt the king fayled and came to naught, farther you ſhall vnderſtand that the Pope had a quarell to the Duke of Ferrara, as well for certaine townes which hee withheld from the Church: as alſo for ſelling of ſalt at Comache without the Popes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which thing beeing his vaſſall hee mought not doe as the Pope ſayde, for the which cauſe hee inuaded his countries, but the king to requite the Popes diſloyaltie and ingratitude towards him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Duke into his protection and defended him againſt the Pope, which not a litle increaſed their euill will.</p>
                  <p>The king alſo to crie quittance with the Pope, <note place="margin">1511.</note> tooke Bolonia from him, which not long beefore hee had deliuered to him, and reſtored it to the <hi>Bentiuoli,</hi> whom alſo hee receiued into his protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by meanes whereof extreame hatred grew beetweene the Pope and the King, ſo farre foorth that the King withdrew his Realme from his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and celebrated a councell at Piſa againſt him, which was afterward tranſported to Milan. And the Pope on the otherſide excomunicated the whole Realme of Fraunce, and celebrated a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at Lateran againſt the king. But not onely ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall but alſo temporall armes were exerciſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, for the Pope hiered the Swyſſers to inuade the Dutchie of Milan the ſecond time, but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9751:17"/>
they being corrupted with French crownes, ſoone returned bome &amp; deluded the Popes hope, which hee perceauing waged a great armie of Spaniards and Italians againſt the king and againſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell (or as hee termed it the Conuenticle) of Piſa, and the king on the other ſide in the name of the ſayde counſell of Piſa ſent a mightie armie againſt the pope, as a Simoniac, a trobler of Chriſtendome, a drunkard; and a periure. And after diuers skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes beetweene the two armies, and ſurpriſes of townes, and ſuch like feates of warre achieued, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewed the great battayle of Rauenna, which was fought vpon Eaſter day. It is written by diuers that Pope Iulius ſeeing his forces iſſew out of Rome, <note place="margin">1512.</note> tooke Peters keyes and threw them into the Riuer, and withall girt himſelfe with a ſword, adding theſe wordes, that ſince Peters keyes could doe him no more ſeruice, hee would ſee if Paules ſword could ſtand him in any better ſteede, which accion of his the learned Melanthon hath properly expreſſed by theſe verſes folowing.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>In Gallum vt fama eſt bellum geſturus a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>cerbum,</l>
                     <l>armatam educit Iulius vrbe manum,</l>
                     <l>accinctus gladio claues in Tibridis amnem</l>
                     <l>proijcit, &amp; ſaeuus talia verba facit:</l>
                     <l>Cum Petri nihil efficiant ad prelia claues</l>
                     <l>auxilio Pauli for ſitan enſis erit:</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which may bee thus Engliſhed.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:9751:18"/>
                     <l>When Iulius againſt the force of Fraunce</l>
                     <l>ſent foorth his troups armed with pike &amp; launce</l>
                     <l>this fury fell inflamde with ire and moode</l>
                     <l>the ſacred keyes into the famous flud</l>
                     <l>of Tyber flange, and tho with might and maine</l>
                     <l>wayuing his glaiue thus ſpake in great diſdaine,</l>
                     <l>ſith Peters keyes auayle naught in this caſe</l>
                     <l>the ſword of Paule ſhall now ſupply their place.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But to returne to the Hiſtorie. In the battaile of Rauenna aboue mentioned, the Pope with his confederats namely the king of Aragon &amp; the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians wer ouerthrowen. But <hi>Monſieur de Foix</hi> the kings nephew &amp; generall of his forces, through his owne to great hardineſſe or rather raſhneſſe, purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his enimies with a ſmall troupe was entrapped and ſlaine, whoſe death the king tooke ſo greuouſly that he wiſhed he had redemed his life with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of al that he held in Italie. The ſaid <hi>de Foix</hi> his death ſo aſtoniſhed the French armie though victorious, that for want of a generall ſufficient to ſupplie his place, they purſewed not the victorie as they ought to hauedone, but gaue their enemies libertie to breath &amp; repaire their forces, which if they had not done, the king mought not onely haue recouered the realme of NAPLES, but alſo haue diſpoſed of all the reſt of Italie as it had pleaſed himſelfe. Rauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na was ſacked in reuenge of <hi>Monſieur de Foix</hi> his death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9751:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>The king celebrateth the counſell of Piſa againſt the Pope, and the Pope the counſell of Later an againſt him. The Pope ſtirreth vp Maximilian the Emperor, the kings of England &amp; Spaine, the venetians, &amp; the ſwiſſers againſt the king. The king loſeth Milan and Genoua. The king of Spaine conquereth Nauarra.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>eter this victorie the king returned to celebrate the counſell of Piſa, and by authoritie thereof to depoſſe the Pope, hauing the Emperour <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in apparance concurring with him, and as ſome report affecting the Papacie for himſelf, &amp; meaning to reſigne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> empire to his nephew Charles though as yet but a childe. Notwithſtanding ſoone after ſecretly hee reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe to the Pope, &amp; vtterly abandoned the French. But the Pope by the ouerthrow which he had receiued at Rauenna, and the great charges he had ſuſtained in theſe wars the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof had lyen vppon his ſhoulders, beeing brought to great pouertie, and doubting alſo what would bee the iſheu of the ſchiſme in the Church: ſought for peace with the king, onely crauing at his hands that hee would relinquiſh the protection of the duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> which the king vtterly refuſing, the Pope fell farther out of pacience with him then euer hee was beefore.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:9751:19"/>
And ſo happely it came to paſſe at that very inſtant for the Popes affaires, that the king of Aragon ſent him a ſecret meſſage to perſwade him to continue the warres againſt the French, aſſuring him of his ayde which thing the king of Aragon dyd, thereby to diſtract the kings forces, while hee inuaded the Realme of Nauarra, which hee was fully reſolued to attempt. And farther <hi>Monſieur de la Paliſſe</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Kings forces after <hi>Monſieur de Foix</hi> his death, was conſtrayned to depart out of Romania with his victorious armie to the defence of the Duchie of Milan fearing that the Swyſſers would inuade it as indeede they dyd, wherefore the Pope by theſe occaſions hauing recouered his ſpirits, and being now more animated againſt the king then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, firſt continued his ſpirituall armes by celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the counſell of Lateran againſt him, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtirred vp not onely the Venetians, but alſo <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperour, the King of England &amp; Spaine, and the Swyſſers to bee his enemies.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Swyſſers as before you haue heard had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned the kings ſeruice becauſe through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe hee would not augment their wages, and were entered into the Popes paye, which his error the king wold willingly haue reformed afterwards, and haue recouered them to his ſeruice againe, but neuer could till his dying day.</p>
                  <p>The king ſeeing all the Princes his neighboures in armes againſt him by the Popes practiſes, was conſtrained to withdraw his forces out of Italie for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9751:19"/>
the defence of his owne Realme by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Pope and the Venetians preuayled ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely in Italie, that they recouered all the townes that were helde by the French namely <hi>Bolonia, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona,</hi> and diuers other, <hi>Parma</hi> alſo and <hi>Placentia</hi> yeelded themſelues to the Pope, yea and the King loſt his Duchie of Milan, which was deliuered to <hi>Maximilian Sforce</hi> (ſonne of Lodouic that died pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in France) vnder the protection and defence of the Swyſſers.</p>
                  <p>The ſtate of Genoua likewiſe reuolted from the king, by meanes of <hi>Ianus Fregoſe</hi> who was made duke thereof, &amp; the Duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> was forced to make his ſubmiſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope and to abandon the French, ſo that the king held nothing at all in Italie ſaue a few caſtles namely that of Milan &amp; the caſtle of Cremona, which continued French ſtill till the next yeare after the battayle of Nouara, when for want of victualls they were forced to yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the Duke of Milans hands, but all the reſt the King loſt almoſt in a moment and withall all his friends, a ſtrange conuerſion of Fortune that the King being conquerour loſt all, and the Pope and the Venetians being conquered wanne all.</p>
                  <p>But in truth they ſayled not with their owne winde but with other mens, for the Realme of Fraunce had at that time to many enemies by the Popes practiſes and to few friends.</p>
                  <p>Now to leaue a while the affaires of Italie and to come to the warres in Fraunce, you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9751:20"/>
that the kings of England and Spaine deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to inuade <hi>Guyenne.</hi> But the king of Spaine pretending the Realme of <hi>Nauarra</hi> to bee of great importance for the defence of the ſayde Countrey of <hi>Guyenne:</hi> perſwaded the engliſh men firſt to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault that, &amp; from thence to enter into <hi>Guyenne,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording wherevnto they did, &amp; ſoone toke it being void of deſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; not expecting any war, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt being achieued, and the ſayde Realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarra deliuered into the king of Spaines hands, the ſaid king with faier words diſmiſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh men, giuing his ſon in law the king of England leaue to inuade <hi>Guyenne</hi> with his owne forces if he would, For he had alredie obtained his pray, by meanes wherof the Engliſh men being diſappointed of his ayde, were forced to returne home. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the king of Fraunce after the Engliſh mens departure, attempted to recouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid realme of <hi>Nauarra:</hi> yet could he not doe it becauſe of his great affaires elſe where.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pope Iulius dyeth, Leo the tenth ſuccedeth, the King ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth truce with the King of Spaine, &amp; being confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated with the Venecians recouereth Milan &amp; Geno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, which notwithſtanding preſently after the battaile of Nouarahee loſeth againe. The Venetians are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen nere to Vincenſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>ABout this time died Pope <hi>Iulius,</hi> to whome ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth of the houſe of <hi>Medices,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1513.</note>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9751:20"/>
which fell out well for the kings affaires, for Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> while he liued, ſo animated all the Princes of Chriſtendome againſt the King, that none of them would encline to make peace or truce with him, but after his death the Kings affaires began to haue a better courſe, for notwithſtanding that Pope <hi>Leo</hi> were not frend to the French, but had iuſt cauſe to hate them, firſt becauſe of the ſchiſme in the Church maintained by them, ſecondarily becauſe by them <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Medices</hi> his brother and their whole houſe was ouerthrowen and chaced out of <hi>Florence,</hi> as in the warrs of <hi>Charles</hi> the eight mention is alreadie made, and laſtly becauſe him ſelfe was taken priſoner by them at the battaile of <hi>Rauenna</hi> being than Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> Legat: yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued he not ſo deadly an enemie to them, nor ſuch an annimater of Chriſtian Princes againſt them as his predeceſſor had been, all the which proceded of the Popes owne diſpoſition, who was a Prince by nature more enclined to pleaſures than to warrs, by meanes whereof the King, burning with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to recouer his Duchie of <hi>Milan</hi> (the rather becauſe the Caſtles of Milan and Cremona held yet for him as before you haue heard) ſought firſt to make truce with the King of Spaine, which the ſayd King eaſelie enclined to, to the ende that in the meane tyme without any impediment of Fraunce he mought ſetle his late conqueſt of the Realme of <hi>Nauarra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:9751:21"/>
Farther the king entered alſo into league with the Venetians who promiſed to ayde him with 800 men of armes, 1500 light horſe, and 10000 foote men, for the recouerie of <hi>Aſt, Genoua,</hi> &amp; the Duchie of Milan, and hee promiſed to ayde them till they had recouered all that they held in Lombardie, and in the <hi>Marca Treuiſana</hi> before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> league of <hi>Cambray.</hi> Thus the king being ioyned with the Venetians, &amp; in truce with the king of Aragon, inuaded the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of Milan with a mightie armie, and firſt reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered Genoua, and then all the Duchie of Milan ſaue Nouara and Coma, which held yet for <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian Sforce,</hi> Farther the French armie vnder the leading of <hi>Trimouille</hi> went and beeſieged Nouara, but this their good ſucceſſe in the beginning was ouerthrowen in the twinkeling of an eye, for you ſhall vnderſtand that the Swyſſers who had bound themſelues to the defence of the ſayde Duchie of Milan as before you haue heard, came to leauie the ſiege of Nouara, &amp; had the french in ſo great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that they aſſaulted them vpon a ſodaine, and defeated them in their owne camp, which was one of the nobleſt victories that euer any nation obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                  <p>This battaile is called the battayle of Nouara. After this victorie all the Duchie of Milan reuolted in a moment, chaced away the French, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the obedience of <hi>Maximilian Sforce,</hi> and the king by this ouerthrow, loſt his honor, his treaſure, and all that he held in Italie as well Genoua as the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9751:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
whole Duchie of Milan, yea and the Caſtels of Milan &amp; Cremona which in all theſe troubles had ſtill continued French ſeing themſelues now in vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſpaire of ſuccors and beeing in extreame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of victualls were yeelded into the Duke of Milans hands, and the Kings armie in great feare and diſtreſſe returned into Piemont.</p>
                  <p>The Venetian forces vnder the leading of Aluiana were comming to ioyne with the French, but hearing of the ouerthrow they retired to Pado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, whether the Viceroy of NAPLES and PROSPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RO COVLONNE beeing in pay with the Pope and the duke of Milan went to beſiege them, but not beeing able to take the towne, they leuyed theyr ſiege, and then ALVIANA iſſewing out of the towne purſewed them and charged them, which charge they valyauntly receaued, &amp; through the vertue of the Spaniſh footmen and cowardiſe of the Italian footemen the Venetian armie was ouerthrowen, and loſt all their artilery &amp; cariagde, and ALVIANA retired to Treuiſa.</p>
                  <p>This battayle was fought nere to Vincenſe and the Venetians loſt in it 400. men of armes, and 4000. ſootemen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9751:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>The king of England ouuerthroweth the french, winneth Therouenne and Tournay. The Swyſſers inuade Burgundy, Queene Anne dyeth, The Pope maketh peace beetweene all theſe Princes. The king marieth the King of Englands ſiſter and dyeth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſame yeare alſo Henry King of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with a mightie armie which the Italians report to haue been to the number of 80000 men inuaded the Realm of Fraunce, &amp; ouerthrew the French in a battaile called <hi>la iournee des eſperons,</hi> wherin the Duke of <hi>Longueuille</hi> with diuers noble men of Fraunce were taken priſoners, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Maximilian</hi> being at that time in perſon in the king of Englands camp, &amp; being alowed dayly by the ſayd king 100 crownes for his diet.</p>
                  <p>The Engliſh men after this battaile toke <hi>Thero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanne</hi> the two and twentith of Auguſt, and from thence by the Emperour <hi>Maximilians</hi> perſuaſion went before <hi>Tournay</hi> which was yelded to them the nine and twentith of September, and hauing defcated in an other battaile in England the <hi>Scots,</hi> the ninth of September, &amp; ſlaine their King in the feeld, who by the perſuaſion of the French had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9751:22"/>
the Realme of England during the Kings abſence in Fraunce: the ſayd king of England tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphantly returned home.</p>
                  <p>Farther the <hi>Swyſſers</hi> being ſecretly hiered with the Popes monie, who loued not the French for the reaſons aboue reherced, inuaded Fraunce alſo on the other ſide, and beſieged <hi>Dijon</hi> in <hi>Burgundy,</hi> into the which <hi>Monſieur de la Trimouille</hi> had put him ſelfe, who doubting the vtter ruine of the Realme of Fraunce ſo many enemies inuading it on all ſides, without any commiſſion from the king made a compoſition with the ſayd <hi>Swyſſers,</hi> more neceſſarie than honorable for the Realme, which was this, that the King ſhould renounce all his right to the Duchie of Milan, and paye them at a day agreed vpon ſix hundreth thouſand Crownes, for the which alſo he deliuered them Hoſtages, and they bound them ſelues onelie to retourne home into their Countrie for that tyme.</p>
                  <p>The Pope was not a litle offended with this theyr returne, but they excuſed the matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receaued not out of England the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that was promiſed them, but in truth their greedineſſe of the ſix hundreth thouſand Crownes aboue mentioned was the principall cauſe of their returne, whereof notwithſtanding their hope was fruſtrate, for the King would not ratifie this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonorable treatie made by Trimouille notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that it were the ſaftie of his Realme,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9751:23"/>
but ſought to content thoſe Swyſſers with other conditions, which they would not accept, but threatned if the treatie were not accompliſhed by a certaine day to ſtrike of the hoſtages heads.</p>
                  <p>About the beginning of the yeare 1514. dyed <note place="margin">1514.</note> Queene Anne of France: Farther you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the Pope being by nature an enimie to the warres and wholie giuen to delights and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, namely to Muſick, to hearing of Playes, and to beeholding of Maskes, bouffons, and ieaſters, yea ſomewhat more then was ſemely for his eſtate: Laboured earneſtly to reconcile theſe Princes and to ende the warres. But the Swyſſers would in no wiſe bee reconciled to the king. Notwithſtanding the truce betwene him &amp; the King of Spaine was continewed, in the which alſo the Emperour <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> contrarie to his promiſe to the king of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland was included, and ratefied the ſayde truce, which vnprincely dealing of the ſayde <hi>Maximilian</hi> cauſed alſo the king of England to encline to peace, which ſoone after namely the ſeauenth of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt by meanes of the Duke of Longueuille being priſoner in England was concluded betweene king Lewis and him, and afterward in October folowing more ſtrongly confirmed by the mariage of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Marie the King of Englands ſiſter with the ſayd King.</p>
                  <p>Thus the king hauing made peace with all his neighbours, and being aſſured of quietneſſe on this ſide the mountaines, turned his thoughts to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9751:23"/>
of that which hee had loſt in Italie, namely the Dutchie of Milan and the eſtate of Genoua. But being in the midſt of his preparation, and inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therevnto by the Pope (though not ſincerly as ſome thought:) ſodaine death which cutteth of all worldly cogitations ſeazed vpon him, for while hee tooke to extreame pleaſure in the excelent beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his young wife, without regard either of his age or the weakneſſe of his complexion, hee was aſſaulted by a feuer, wherevnto a fluxe being ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hee departed almoſt ſodainely out of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life the firſt day of Ianuarie in the yeere 1515. after the Ducche and Italian computation who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the yeare at newyerſtide, but 1514. according to the French, who begin it not till Eaſter. This king liued 55. yeeres, and raigned 17.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 10. <hi>A diſcourſe of certaine vertues and vices of King Lewis the twelfth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etweene this King Lewis and Pope Iulius the 2. aboue mentioned was deadly hatred, as by the Hiſtorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue written eaſely you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, ſo farre foorth that they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewed one an other not onely with armes but alſo with gybes &amp; ſcoffes. The Pope ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the king of ſacriledge wherevnto the king an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9751:24"/>
that it was moſt abſurde for him to accuſe an other of ſacrilige that miantained his eſtate one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſale of holy things, for the Pope made money of al eccleſiaſticall liuings &amp; dignities, againe when the king heard that the Pope had extremely curſed him hee aunſwered that this was a Pope made to curſe but not to pray, ſarther the Pope called the french Micturi vinos, that is to ſay wine piſſers, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereby their immoderate drincking of wyne, which (as he ſaid) iſſued as it entered, but this gibe euell beſemed the Pope being himſelfe more giuen to drinke then any man in his time. But the French partly to requite this ſcoffe, &amp; partly to content the king, made theſe verſes of the Pope.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Patria cui Genua eſt, genitricem Graecia, partum</l>
                     <l>Pontus &amp; vnda dedit, qui bonus eſse poteſt?</l>
                     <l>ſunt vani Ligures, mendax eſt Graecia, ponto</l>
                     <l>nulla fides, malus eſt haec tria quis quis hahet.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which you may thus Engliſh.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Whoſe countrie is liguria, whoſe damme of Greekiſh bloud</l>
                     <l>whoſe cradle is the ſourging ſeas, can ought in him be good?</l>
                     <l>Ligurians are counted vaine, Greekes lyers ſo I finde,</l>
                     <l>the ſea inconſtant, all theſe three hath <hi>Iulius</hi> by kinde.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But theſe verſes are anſwered thus on the Popes beehalfe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9751:24"/>
                     <l>Eſt venus orta mari, Graium ſapientia, ſolers</l>
                     <l>ingenium eſt ligurum, qui malus eſse poteſt?</l>
                     <l>cui genus vt veneri, a Graijs ſapientia, ſolers</l>
                     <l>ingenium a Genua eſt? Mome proter<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e tace.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which you may thus Engliſh.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Out of the ſea dame <hi>Venus</hi> ſprang, with learning grece is clad</l>
                     <l>Ligurians are full of wit, how can hee then bee bad?</l>
                     <l>whoſe birth is like a Godeſſes, whoſe learning is of Grece,</l>
                     <l>whoſe wit is of Liguria, iack gyber hold thy peace.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But to returne to king Lewis, he was a prince ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to great varietie of Fortune through the whole courſe of his life, both before he was King &amp; after, but eſpecially towards his later end ſhe moſt froun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon him, as in this briefe diſcourſe of his actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is plainely to bee ſeene, his vices were, in his youth loue of women, and in his age couetouſneſſe, which cauſed him to looſe many opportunities, beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee was a prince wholy gouerned by others, but his good fortune was to fall into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages, and ſuch as gouerned his Realme well. Farther he was alſo charged with ingratitude, both towards his wife who had ſaued his life, and alſo towards ſome with whom hee had liued fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarlie beefore his comming to the crowne, namely the Marſhall <hi>Gyé,</hi> whom alſo hee baniſhed the court, notwithſtanding the great ſeruice that hee had done the Realme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:9751:25"/>
But herein he is partly to be excuſed, for the ſaid Marſhalls baniſhment proceeded principally from the Queene who hated him extreamlie, becauſe the ſayde marſhall had oncc ſtayed hir cariage vpon the Riuer of Loyre, wherein ſhe had packed vp all the kings principall Iuells, Plate, and other things of great price, and the which ſhee was conueighing downe the ſayde Riuer to Nantes, the King being at that time very ſick and in great daunger of death. This king was alſo giuen to ſuſpicions, but that is a fault all princes are ſubject to, eſpecially all thoſe that be wiſe, on the other ſide this king was beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with many goodly vertues, firſt hee was ſo lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and carefull of his people, that in all his forraine warres hee could neuer be induced to increaſe his impoſitions vpon his ſubiects, true it is that when he was inuaded in his owne Realme, he was forced to leauie of them ſomewhat more then ordinarie, for the which his milde gouernment he was called Pater patriae, ſo iuſta Prince he was (where the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of his affaires enforced him not to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie) that the Archduc Philip committed to him at his death the gouernment of his ſonne Charles, omitting both his owne father and his father in law, being both Graundfathers to the ſaid Childe, which charge king Lewis moſt princely performed as well in the education of the ſayde Charles after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Emperour, as alſo in the preſeruation of all his eſtate.</p>
                  <p>Farther he was a prince voide of all pride, affable,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9751:25"/>
and curteous to all men, and liuing in great qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe &amp; mildeneſſe, with thoſe that were famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar with him, and the ſooneſt forgetting all iniuries paſt, ſo that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare him to any prince then to the Emperour ADRIAN, whoſe pleaſant an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres and Apophthegmes being voide of all ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilitie hee was alſo much addicted vnto, ſome of the which becauſe they bee worthie of memorie I will be bould to rehearſe. Hee had in king Charles his time beene euell vſed by diuers, of whom hee was aduiſed to take reuenge at his comming to the crowne, wherevnto hee aunſwered that it became not a king of Fraunce to reuenge the iniuries done to a Duke of Orleans.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe looking vppon the roule of King Charles his ſeruaunts, he found two that had been his deadly enimies in King Charles his time, vpon each of whoſe names he made a croſſe, wherewith they being in a wonderfull perplexitie, ſuppoſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> galowes to be prepared for them, which their feare being diſcouered to the king: he ſent them word to bee of good cheare, for hee had croſſed all their euell deedes out of his remembraunce, hee vſed to ſay that the condition of horſſes was much worſe then Aſſes, for Horſſes were killed vp in running poſt to Rome to fetch liuing for Aſſes, meaning vnlearned prelats, when the Queene his wife by importunitie thought to bring to paſſe a mariage betwene hir daughter Claude &amp; Archduc Charles afterwards Emperour, the king told hir that ſhee
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9751:26"/>
ſought to make a mariage betwene Cats and Mice. Againe when a certaine courtier complained grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly of his wiues vnchaſtneſſe, the king hearing thereof bad him bee of good cheare, for hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected his wyues incontinencie or the Popes curſe ſhould neuer ſleepe quiet night. Diuers other ſuch like ſayings of his I could rehearce which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie I ouerpaſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>FRANCIS THE FIRST OF <hi>that name King of Fraunce.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>King Francis commeth to the crowne, ſurpriſeth Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Colonna, vanquiſheth the Swyſſers, recouereth Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. The Pope and hee meete at Bolonia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O Lewis the twelfth ſucceded King Francis y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, beeing both his ſonne <note place="margin">1515.</note> in law and the next of his bloud, a Prince of yong yeares, but of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſonage &amp; great magnanimitie, who finding a mighty armie in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, that his predeceſſor had leuied to inuade the Duchie of Milan, &amp; burning with no leſſe deſier to recouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid duchie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his predeceſſor had done, determined to loſe no time but hauing renewed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> league made by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> late king with <hi>Henry</hi> king of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and with the ſelfe ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions, &amp; likewiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9751:26"/>
with the Venetians, and receaued homage at Paris by the Earle of Naſſau of the Archduc Charles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Eemperor for Flaunders, and hauing alſo made peace with him with promes of mariage bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſaid Charles and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lady Renee daughter to king Lewis &amp; ſiſter to the Queene, and withall Genoua beeing reduced to his obedience by the meanes of <hi>Octauian Fregoſe</hi> Duke therof, who ſtood in continuall feare of the Duke of Milan and the Swyſſers: hee preſently marched with his armie towards the mountaines. <hi>Maximilian</hi> duke of Milan ſeing the tempeſt that hunge ouer his head, ſent to the Swyſſers and to Pope Leo for aide. The Pope ſent to his ayde <hi>Proſpero Coulonna</hi> with 1500. horſe, whom the french vpon a ſodaine (as they paſſed the Alpes by a ſecret way neuer paſſed before by horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) ſurpriſed &amp; toke priſoner at villa francha, and defeated al his troupes. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence the king march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; beeſieged <hi>Nouara</hi> which yeelded vnto him, as did alſo <hi>Alexandria, Tortona &amp; Pauia</hi> with diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther townes: Farther to make his conqueſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eaſier, he practiſed to pacifie with monie the Swiffers who were bound to the defence of the duchie of Milan as before you haue heard, &amp; to cauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to returne home, wherevnto they agreed, and rceaued ſome ſmall part of the kings money in ſuch ſort that the king accompted his conqueſt to bee at an ende. But the Cardinall of Syon ſo preached vnto them their league made with the Duke of Milan, that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their mindes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:9751:27"/>
And when the king thought they had beene telling their money, they came in a great furie and inuaded his armie, which valiantly receaued their charge. And what with force of canon ſhot, and valour of the <hi>Gendarmerie</hi> of France (who made a <note place="margin">1515.</note> mends this day for their cowardiſe at the battell of <hi>Nouara)</hi> but eſpecially through the great magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the king himſelfe, they were repulſed, and ſo hewed in pieces two dayes together (for ſo long the battayle endured) that in the ende they were put to flight, &amp; ſlaine at the leaſt 16000. of them, &amp; their courages ſo daunted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after this they reigned not ouer princes as before times they had done.</p>
                  <p>This battaile is called the battaile of Marignian, which was fought the thirteenth of September in the yeare 1515. and was ſo bloudie on both ſides, that Maſter Iames of Treuoul who had beene in nineteene battayles, reported this to haue beene a battayle of Gyaunts, and all the other eighteene that hee had been in, in compariſon of this to haue beene but battailes of boyes.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Swyſſers purpoſe was if they had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne the king, to haue diſpoſed at theyr plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Duchie of Milan which wholy depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon them. But their hope was fruſtrate, and being thus vanquiſhed they returned home, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon Maximilian Sforce Duke of Milan, and the whole Countrey yeelded to the king. The ſayde <hi>Maximilian</hi> was ſent into Fraunce, where hee was ſo honorably entertained of the King, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9751:27"/>
notwithſtanding that he mought afterwards haue returned home, yet would he neuer ſo do, alledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that hee was deliuered from the ſeruitude of the Swyſſers, the euell vſage of the Emperour, and the trecherie of the Spaniards, wherfore hee choſe rather to remaine in France, wher he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till his death, which happened in the yeare 1530. After this victorie the Pope and all the Princes of Italie ſought the kings amitie, ſo far forth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pope met with him at <hi>Bolonia,</hi> &amp; yeelded vnto him <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placencia</hi> as members of the Duchie of Milan, which <hi>Iulius</hi> his predeceſſor had taken before as the poſſeſſions of the Church. About the ende of this yeare dyed the valyaunt Captaine Aluiane, hauing done great ſeruice at the battayle of Marignian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned, and was very honorably buried at Venis in the Church of Saint Stephan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 2. <hi>The King returneth into Fraunce, recouereth the Swiſſers to his ſeruice, Ferdinande King of Spaine dyeth. Maximilian the Emperour inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Duchie of Milan. The Venetians reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Breſſa &amp; Verona, a treatie betwene the king and Charles king of Caſtile at Noyon. The wars of Vrbine, Luther preacheth againſt the Pope.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE King at his retourne into Fraunce leſt the <note place="margin">1516.</note> Duke of Burbon gouernour of Milan, and ſo ſoone as hee was come into his Realme practiſed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9751:28"/>
to recouer the <hi>Swyſſers</hi> to his ſeruice, and to make a new league with them, which alſo was brought to paſſe, and they promiſed from time to time to ayde him in his warrs againſt all men, the Pope and the Empire onelie excepted. But fiue of theyr Cantons would not agree to this accord at this time. Notwithſtanding about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of this yeare theſe fiue alſo were contented to enter into league with him, but not ſo far foorth as the other eight, for they entered into a league offenſiue with the King, but theſe fiue onely for the defence of his owne eſtates.</p>
                  <p>In this yeare dyed <hi>Ferdinande</hi> king of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and <hi>Conſalue</hi> otherwiſe ſurnamed the great Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, about a moneth before him. The Duke of <hi>Borbon</hi> gouernour of <hi>Milan</hi> for the King, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the kings league with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> ſent vnto them vnder the leading of Monſieur <hi>de Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trech</hi> 3000. footemen and 1000. horſe to recouer <hi>Breſſa</hi> &amp; <hi>Verona.</hi> But becauſe the Emperour <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imilian</hi> enuying the kings great ſucceſſe (as did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the king of England) leauied men of the fiue Swyſſer Cantons that were as yet not in league with the king, and hauing receaued 50000. angels of the king of England, and being confederated with Francis Sforce brother to Maximilian aboue mentioned: inuaded the Duchie of Milan with a mightie armie of Swyſſers, Lanceknights, and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards: the ſayd <hi>Lautrech</hi> was conſtrained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe with his forces to Milan.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9751:28"/>
The ſayd Maximilian came before Milan with this mightie armie, but being by nature verie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and hauing receaued out of England a new ſupply of monie, he ſodainly gaue forth that he was aduertiſed of the king of Hungaries death, which occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuoked him of neceſſitie into Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne, wherevppon preſently he diſmiſſed his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie without doing any matter of moment and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted home hauing filled his baggs with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of Englands angells. After his departure Lautrech re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned againe to ayd the Venetians, who recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Breſſa and Verona. Farther Charles Duke of Auſtrich, &amp; by his grandfathers death king of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings great ſucceſſe, &amp; doubting that he would inuade the realme of Naples which eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that time he mought haue done and was alſo purpoſed to haue done, if the Emperour Maximili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans deſcent into Italie had not ſtaied him, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded peace with the king at Noyon, wher were great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of amitie betwene theſe two princes, &amp; promiſe of mariage betwene the ſaid king of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile &amp; Louyſe the kings daughter, &amp; diuers other articles agreed vpon which neuer wer performed, for the ſaid king of Caſtile ment onely by this diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation to preſerue his realme of Naples, which if the king would haue inuaded he was not at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time in caſe to defend, by reaſon he was not as yet ſetled in his kingdome of Spaine, the people wherof ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med better affected to Ferdinand his brother (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had been bred vp among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) then to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:9751:29"/>
You haue heard beefore how the King and the Pope met at <hi>Bolonia</hi> after the battaile of <hi>Marignian,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1517.</note> where alſo the Pope reſtored to the king <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placentia,</hi> but with this condition that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king ſhould ayde him to chace <hi>Francis Maria de la Rouere</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> owt of the Duchie of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> which alſo the king did in the yeare 1516. And the Pope gaue the ſaide Duchie of <hi>Vrbin</hi> to <hi>Laurens</hi> of <hi>Medices</hi> his nephew, to whom alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more to content the Pope gaue in mariage the lady <hi>Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> heire of the Earledome of <hi>Bouloyne</hi> in France, of the which mariage iſſued <hi>Catherin</hi> of <hi>Medices</hi> queene of france. Notwithſtanding in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare 1517. the ſayde <hi>Francis Maria</hi> recouered his Duchie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine out of the Popes hands, &amp; notwithſtanding that afterwards by aide of the French y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope draue the ſaid <hi>Francis Maria</hi> to a hard co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereby he left the ſaide duchie to the Pope, &amp; was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to take a Penſion in regarde therof: yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he not long in this eſtate, for ſo ſoone as pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> was choſen Pope he reſtored <hi>Francis Maria</hi> to his Duchie of <hi>Vrbin</hi> againe, who quietly enioyed it to his dying day which happened in the yeer 1538. Thus much I thought good to write in this place of the ſucceſſe of this warr of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> becauſe hereafter I meane not to make farther mention thereof.</p>
                  <p>This yeare alſo <hi>Martin Luther</hi> beegan openly to preach againſt the Popes pardons in <hi>Germanie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9751:29"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Maximilian the Emperour dyeth, Charles king of Caſtile ſucceedeth him. The King confederateth himſelfe with the King of England, who reſtoreth Tournay to him. The two Kings meete beetweene Ardres and Calais. The King of England and the Emperor mete alſo together at Calais and Grauelin, a rebellion in Spain.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King perceauing by diuers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent <note place="margin">1518.</note> reaſons that the King of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile ment to performe nothing of that which was promiſed at <hi>Noyon,</hi> and farther vnderſtanding that the Emperour <hi>Maximilian</hi> laboured the electors of the Empire to chooſe king of Romaines the ſayde king of Caſtile his Nephew, a thing greatly diſpleaſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, becauſe the Empire being ioyned to his Patrimoniall ſeniories, the ſayd king of Caſtile ſhould bee ſo mightie, that no Prince in Chriſtendome ſhould bee able to withſtand his power: dyd both with his money and by his miniſters diſſwade the electors from that election, and ſtayed it during <hi>Maximilians</hi> lyfe.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding after the ſayde <hi>Maximilians</hi> death which happened the twelfth of Ianuary 1519 after the Duch and Italian accompt, who beginne the yeare at Newyerſtide, but 1518. after the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9751:30"/>
French who begin it not till Eaſter, the ſaid Charles king of Caſtile was elected Emperour, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the impediments of the king, and the great ſute both he and his friends had made to obtaine the Empire for himſelfe, but god had otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of it. Wherefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king hauing failed of his hope for the obtaining of the Empire, and ſeeing the powre of the Emperour elect ſo greatly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: determined to enter into a ſtraight confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie &amp; alliance with the king of England, to whom he ſent Ambaſſadors to treate of a mariage betwen <note place="margin">1519.</note> their children, which was concluded and as well performed as the other treatiſe of mariage with the king of Caſtile had bene. Farther the king labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the king of England to reſtore Tournay vnto him becauſe it was a towne that ſerued the Engliſh men to ſmall purpoſe, being far from their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the defence thereof being yearely to the King of England a great charge, but ſtoode verie commodiouſly for the king to offend at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Emperour in his low cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries, which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſo earneſtly purſued that for the ſumme of 400000. crownes the towne was deliuered into the kings hands, and a ſtraight league concluded betwene the king of England and him, and it was agreed that the next yeare an enteruiew ſhould be of the two kings betwen Calais and Ardres, which alſo was accompliſhed accordingly, with ſo great <note place="margin">1520.</note> triumph &amp; brauerie on both ſides, that the French called the place of the enteruiew <hi>Le Camp de drap
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9751:30"/>
d'or:</hi> and with ſo great demonſtrations of loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Princes, that the like was not ſeene in many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeares before. For beſides the roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all &amp; ſumptuous entertainment that they gaue each to other, ſuch brotherly loue and aſſurance was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene them, that in one day the two kings went &amp; dined each with others Queene, and farther one morning verie earely the king of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce came with a ſmall traine to Guyſnes before the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was ſtirring, and tould him that he was come to yeld him ſelfe his priſoner in his Caſtle of Guyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whereunto the King of England anſwered that he was come to take his hart his priſoner which was a verie readie &amp; an apt anſwere. To conclude ſuch ſignes of perfect loue &amp; amitie paſſed betwen theſe two princes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of 15. or 16. dayes (for ſo long they were together) that all men thought their friendſhip to be indiſſoluble, &amp; that war could neuer ariſe betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it happened otherwiſe afterwards, whereby it appereth that he ſpake truth that ſaid <hi>Princes amitie to be no inheritance.</hi> Not long after this enteruiew aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, the new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour elect ariued in England, where contrarie to the king of Fraunce his expectation, he was moſt honorably receaued, in ſuch ſort that the King of England accompanied him to Calais &amp; afterwards to Grauelin, where they were together a certaine ſpace in great friendſhip and fraternitie, and where diuers things were concluded betwene them no whit to the contentation of the King of Fraunce.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9751:31"/>
Among other articles this was one, that what controuerſie ſoeuer happened beetweene the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and the King, the King of England ſhould bee the iudge thereof; which article beecauſe the king would not agre vnto, the king of England toke occaſion to become his enemie therevpon.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the warres brake not out betwene them this yeare, as well becauſe they had no apparant quarell on either ſide, as alſo becauſe they had not as yet made their prouiſions for the warres, beeſides that Spaine was troubled with a great rebellion which the Spaniards called <hi>La San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta giunta</hi> which could not bee appeaſed till the next yeare, that feare of the forraine enemy name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the French inuading Spaine, cauſed the Spaniards to forget all the domeſticall diſſentions, and to attend to the defence of their countrey.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 4. <hi>VVars betwene the king &amp; the Emperour. The French conquer Nauarre and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently loſe it againe. The Imperials winne many places from the French in the Duchie of Milan. The French win Fontarabia. Naſſau inuadeth Picar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. The Emperour recouereth Tournay.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BVt to proceede, the long diſſembled euill will <note place="margin">1521.</note> betweene theſe two mightie Princes could no longer be hidden, but like a fier that had long been ſmothered brake ſodainely forth into a great
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9751:31"/>
flame, partly by the ſolicitation of the King of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland &amp; <hi>Francis Sforce,</hi> and partly by a quarell that happened betweene <hi>Robert de la Marche</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur d'Emeriez</hi> about a Caſtell called <hi>Hiergie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>la Marche</hi> beeing in league with the King &amp; in his protection, inuaded his enemy with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine french forces, and deſtroyed certaine villages within the Emperours dominions, wherewith the Emperour being much grieued, toke vpon him the defence of <hi>de' Emeriez</hi> his ſubiect, and vpon this occaſion began the warrs in thoſe parts the flames whereof in a moment ſpred ouer all theſe princes dominions, for the king perceauing the Emperors &amp; the king of Englands euell diſpoſition towardes him, determined while the Emperour was troubled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue mentioned rebellion in Spaine which as yet was vnpacefed, to inuade the realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarra, and to reſtore it to Henry the trew king ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe father, <hi>Ferdinande</hi> king of Spaine had wrongfully taken it as beefore you haue heard.</p>
                  <p>The French armie at the firſt had good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, &amp; recouered in effect the whole Realme. But the French Captains puffed vp with pride becauſe of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt, &amp; moued alſo with couetouſneſſe, hoping to obtaine ſome goodly bootie in Spaine, beecauſe of the great diuiſion the countrey was in, entered into the Realme as farre as the Groyne, which their inuaſion vnited the Spainards toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that beefore were in diuiſion, in ſuch ſort that they ſet vpon the French, and not onely chaced
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9751:32"/>
them out of Spaine, but alſo purſewing them far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther entered into Nauarra, from whence the Kings armie beeing in deſtreſſe both of victuals &amp; money was forced to retire, &amp; loſt all the places which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid realme as eaſely as they had wonne them: Farther the Emperours forces incited by this victorie paſſed farther into France, and ſpoyled many places in the countrey, and then in ſaftie returned home. In Italie alſo the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and his confederats, toke diuers places in the Duchie of Milan, and made ſharp warres vpon the king there, wherewith the king being greatly irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and purpoſing to draw the Emperour from the warres in Italie, to looke neerer home, namely into Spaine, ſent an armie into <hi>Biſcay,</hi> &amp; toke <hi>Fontarabia,</hi> and fortified it and held it till the yeare 1523. when the Spaniards recouered it againe as hereafter you ſhall heare. And on an other ſide alſo the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſorces vnder the leading of the Earle of <hi>Naſſau</hi> inuaded <hi>Picardie,</hi> raſed <hi>Muſancourt,</hi> toke <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and beſieged <hi>Meziers</hi> which Captaine <hi>Bayarde</hi> valiantly defended againſt him. Then the King with a mightie armie came downe in perſon into <hi>Picardie,</hi> purpoſing to fight with the ſayde Earle of <hi>Naſſau,</hi> but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaw that he would by no meanes bee drawen to the battaile, the King departed lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his armie vnder the charge of the Duke of <hi>Bourbon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> who tooke <hi>Heſdin</hi> &amp; diuers other townes.</p>
                  <p>But the king himſelfe after his departure out of <hi>Picardie</hi> entered into <hi>Burgundie,</hi> where he toke and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9751:32"/>
ſpoyled diuers townes, while the Emperour on the other ſide recouered <hi>Tournay</hi> which had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued French till this time, euer ſince it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to them by the king of England who toke it in the time of King LEVVIS the twelfth as bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue heard, and thus proceded the warrs in theſe parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Pope Leo falleth from the King to the Emperour. The Imperials winne Milan and ſoone after alſo Genoua. Pope Leo dyeth, Adrian the ſixth ſuccedeth. The Swyſſers furiouſly inuading the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als camp are vanquiſhed. The King of England defieth the King by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours procurement. The Turke win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Ile of Rhodes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to returne to the warrs of Italie, Pope <hi>Leo</hi> ſeing the Emperours great ſucceſſe, began to ſtraunge his mind from the king, and ſecretly entered into league with the ſaid Emperour, pretending diuers iniuries done vnto him by the kings Miniſters in the Duchie of Milan, but indede burning with a deſire to recouer Parma and Placentia, which himſelfe as you haue heard had after the battaile of Marignian yeelded to the king.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:9751:33"/>
So the Pope, the Emperour, and <hi>Francis Sforce</hi> ioyned together againſt the king, and tooke Milan (which <hi>Monſieur de Lautrech</hi> defended againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as long as hee could) and afterwards alſo <hi>Come, Cremona, Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Pauia.</hi> Notwithſtanding <hi>Cremona</hi> the ſayd Lautrech recouered ſoone after againe and the Caſtell of Milan held ſtill for the king.</p>
                  <p>While theſe warres in the Duchie of Milan endured dyed Pope Leo, and in fauour of the Emperour, <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixth a Holander &amp; the ſaide Emperours ſcholemaſter, notwithſtanding that he were at that time abſent in Spaine was choſen Pope. The French beeing renforced with new <note place="margin">1522.</note> ſupplies namely with 10000. Swyſſers entred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the Duchie of Milan, and came before Milan &amp; <hi>Pauia,</hi> which were ſo defended againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by <hi>Proſpero Colonna,</hi> that they were forced to depart and abandon their ſiege. Wherevpon the Swyſſers that ſerued in the kings armie, being wearie of the warres came to <hi>Monſieur de Lautrech</hi> and tould him that except he would fight with the enemie the next day they would depart home, which the ſayd <hi>Lautrech</hi> at the firſt refuſed to doe, alledging the great diſaduantage they ſhould fight with, becauſe they muſt of force aſſault y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies in their camp, where <hi>Proſpero Colonna</hi> and the Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> were ſo ſtrongly fortefied y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could not but vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſpaire of the victorie. But notwithſtanding all theſe reaſons fight hee muſt with all theſe diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntages,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9751:33"/>
the Swyſſers hoping of as good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe heere as they had againſt the French, when they aſſaulted them in their campe at Nouara. But the iſſue fell out cleane contrarie, for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that theſe Swyſſers furiouſly aſſaulted the enemies campe, yet were they repulſed and a great number of them ſlaine, the French in very good order retiring themſelues.</p>
                  <p>This battaile is called the battaile of <hi>Bicocque.</hi> The Swiſſers after the battaile returned home not once taking their leaue of Lautrech, who alſo hauing loſt the whole Duchie of Milan through this mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous raſhneſſe of the Swyſſers retourned into Fraunce to the king, leauing at his departure Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Leſcun his brother gouernour in Italie of thoſe Peices that held yet for the king, but for want both of men and money, ſeruice hee could doe none, ſo that the Imperials tooke Cremona and ſoone after alſo Genoua, and laſtly the Caſtle of Milan was alſo yeelded to them. The Emperour whoſe affaires fell out according to his deſire paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into Spaine, &amp; by the way landed in England and ſo preuayled with king Henry that hee decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe Imperiall, and ſent a Herrault to defie the king.</p>
                  <p>Farther they both ſent Ambaſſadors to Venis to diſſwade them from the kings friendſhip and to perſwade them to enter into league with them, which alſo they obtayned in the ende. But you ſhall vnderſtand that while theſe Chriſtian Princes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9751:34"/>
warred thus one vppon an other, the Turke to the reproch of them all wan the Ile of Rhodes being as it were the bulwark of all Chriſtendome. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the great maſter of the Rhodes ſent to all theſe Princes for ayde: yet were they ſo inflamed one againſt another, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they preferred theyr owne priuate quarells beefore the publique defence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 6. <hi>The Venetians forſake the King, The Duke of Bourbon falleth alſo from him, The Emperour inuadeth Biſcay, recouereth Fontarabia, The King of England in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uadeth Picardie. Bourbon inuadeth Burgundie. Boniuet inuadeth Milan for the king but with euell ſucceſſe. Pope Adrian dyeth, Clement the ſeuenth ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth. The Emperour inuadeth Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce but with euell ſucceſſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE treatie aboue mentioned with the Venetians was ſo earneſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued <note place="margin">1523.</note> that in the ende they forſoke the king, &amp; entered into league with the Emperour, with the Archduc <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinande</hi> his brother, and with Francis Sforce inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the Emperour Duke of Milan, ſo that it was thought the king would now attempt no thing in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9751:34"/>
Italie, hauing ſo many enimies, &amp; his eſpecial frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds namely the Venetians being become his foes, but it fell otherwiſe out as hereafter you ſhall heare.</p>
                  <p>In the meane time Pope Adrian being come out of Spaine into Italie compounded the controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betwene the Duke of Ferrare and the Church, and endeuoured to reconcile all thoſe Princes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether and to conuert their Armes againſt the Turke, but all in vaine.</p>
                  <p>About this tyme alſo Charles Duke of Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon Conſtable of Fraunce and the greateſt prince in the Realme reuolted from the king to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Diuers cauſes are alleadged by diuers men of his reuolt. But I think ambition to haue bene the onely cauſe thereof, For he being a Prince of great courage, and greatly beloued in the Realme, was perſwaded that he could haue drawen the greateſt part of the Realme after him, and was promiſed in mariage Elenor the Emperours ſiſter widow of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuell king of Portugale, and to haue the earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Prouince conquered by the armes of the Emperour and the King of England, and erected into a Kingdome deliuered to him. And he for his part promiſed if the Emperour would giue him the leading of twelue thouſand Lancknights to conquere all Burgundie from the king, and to reſtore it to the ſayde Emperour who claimed it as heire to Charles the laſt Duke of Burgundie ſlaine by the Swyſſers at the battaile of Naucy in the yeare 1476.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9751:35"/>
Thus oftentime are the nobleſt witts ſo drowned with an ouergreat opinion of themſelues, that they hould thoſe enterpriſes for eaſie which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede impoſſible to be atchieued.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the Emperour vſed his help in the warres, and hee ſhewed extreame hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king and his countrey all the time of his life, for the which moſt men blame him and few commend him. The Emperour hauing ſtirred vp almoſt all the Princes of Chriſtendome againſt the king, ment to aſſault him on all ſides, and ſo to deſtract his forces that he ſhould haue enough to doe to defend his owne, and by that meanes not bee able to offend him in Italie. Wherefore firſt hee ſent an armie to inuade Biſcay which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged Bayonne but could not take it, but Fonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia they recouered from the French, God ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of this matter that each partie ſhould hould their owne and no more: on the other ſide the king of England ſent the Duke of Suffolke with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie armie to inuade Picardie. But God hauing commiſeration as it is to be thought of the poore Realme of Fraunce, cauſed the ſayde Engliſh armie for want of victualles and money to retourne home without any matter of moment done.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of Bourbon likewiſe inuading Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundie had no better ſucceſſe, for beeing ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with his twelue thouſand Lansknights into the countrey, both his money and his intelligences
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:9751:35"/>
fayled him, and his ſouldiours wanting pay left him, and the moſt part of them went to ſerue the king.</p>
                  <p>Thus God fought for the king as long as hee ſtoode vpon the defence of his owne Realme, but out of his owne Realme his ſucceſſe was farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. God as it is to be thought puniſhing his ambition in mouing vnneceſſary warrs abroad to trouble the ſtate of Italie, and not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his large, ritch, and floriſhing Realme at home. For you ſhall vnderſtand that at this time he was him ſelfe paſſing with a mightie army into Italie to recouer the Duchie of Milan, as though without Milan the king of Fraunce were not worthie the name of king. And notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that <hi>Bourbons</hi> reuolt and the inuaſions aboue mentioned ſtayed his owne perſon in Fraunce: yet his armie conſiſting of 34000. men, hee ſent into Italie vnder the leading of the Admirall <hi>Boniuet,</hi> to recouer the ſayd Duchie of Milan.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proſpero Colonna</hi> being gouernour of Milan for the Emperour and <hi>Francis Sforce</hi> met with this French armie at the Riuer of <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſin</hi> with purpoſe to ſtoppe their paſſage, but that notwithſtanding they paſſed the riuer and <hi>Proſpero</hi> was forced to retire to Milan, whether if <hi>Boniuet</hi> had preſently ſolowed him and giuen him no leaſure to fortefie the towne, it is thought he mought haue taken it without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. But the actions of great ſouldiers are not to bee cenſured by the iudgement of the vulgare
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9751:36"/>
ſort many reaſons &amp; great daungers mought moue him to forbeare to giue <hi>Proſpero</hi> the chace &amp; attempt to take the towne by force, which he being generall concealed to himſelfe, and deliuered not to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of men. About this time dyed Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> &amp; to him ſucceded <hi>Iulius</hi> Cardinall of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dices</hi> by the name of <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeuenth. The French armie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned vnder the leading of <hi>Boniuet</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Milan during the which ſiege <hi>Proſpero Coulonne</hi> dyed in his bed, &amp; to the reliefe of the towne came the Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> with new ſupplies, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Duke of <hi>Bourbon</hi> (hauing fayled of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe in <hi>Burgundie)</hi> with 7000. Landsknights leuied in <hi>Allmaigne</hi> by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the Emperours brother, by meanes whereof (the Venetians alſo ioyning with the Imperials, and the Swyſſers that came to the ſuccour of the French, traiterouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to paſſe the riuer of <hi>Seuze</hi> &amp; to ioine with the Admirals armie) the French were forced not onely to abandon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiege, but alſo with great loſſe of men, &amp; eſpecially of the noble captaine <hi>Bayarde</hi> to retire into France, <hi>Bourbon</hi> and the Imperials continually charging them on the backe as they marched. This ſucceſſe had the king in Italie, and no better had the Emperour in Fraunce, who about the ende of this yeare inuaded in perſon with a mightie armie the Realme of Fraunce from the frontiers of Spaine, ſuppoſing the ſmall exploict done beefore <hi>Bayonne</hi> to haue proceded from the negligence of his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; <hi>Sauueterre</hi> he tooke a place of ſmall impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9751:36"/>
which being done, his courage being greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his abilitie to entertaine ſo mightie an armie &amp; lacking both money &amp; victuals which could hardly folow him in thoſe ſtraight paſſages, beeſides that the harde weather comming on which is verie terrible in that rockie, and mountaine countrey: he was forced to diſmiſſe his armie &amp; returne home, &amp; to abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this enterpriſe, which he had attempted againſt the aduice of all his beſt ſouldiours and Captaines.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Queene Claude of France dieth, Bourbon inuadeth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, but is ſoone forced to retire, The king inuadeth Milan, and is taken priſoner at the battaile of Pauia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN Iulie in the yeare 1524. dyed Queene <hi>Claude</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1524.</note> at <hi>Bloys</hi> greatly to the kings griefe, for ſhe was a moſt wiſe and vertuous Ladie. The Imperials hauing chaced the French armie cleane out of the Duchie of Milan as before you haue heard, but knowing the kings magnanimitie to bee ſuch that hee would not faile to attempt the recouery therof, determined to inuade him firſt in his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, thereby to cauſe him to attend to the defence of his owne Realme, &amp; to ſtay him from trobling the Emperour on the other ſide of the mountains. Wherefore the Duke of Bourbon with a mightie armie entered into Prouince promiſing the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to worke wonders there for his ſeruice, and beſieged <hi>Marſeilles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:9751:37"/>
But the king in perſon with a great armie came to ſuccour the towne, wherevpon <hi>Bourbon</hi> for all his great bragges and the Imperials, were forced to leuic their ſiege, and in great haſt retired to Milan, whether the king with his whole armie folowed them, &amp; ſoone recouered Milan and in a manner the whole countrie, except Pauia, before the which he went and layde his ſiege. Wherevpon the Pope entered into league with him, and the Swyſſers who the laſt yeare had traiterouſly refuſed to ioyne with the Admirall <hi>Boniuets</hi> armie and had abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the French as before you haue heard, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the kings ſeruice againe.</p>
                  <p>But while the king lay beefore the ſiege of Pauia and had brought it to extreame neceſſitie. <hi>Bourbon</hi> went into <hi>Germanie,</hi> and brought with him 6000. footemen and 2000. horſe: Farther 6000. Rhetians being corrupted by the Imperials aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned the kings campe and returned home, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo certaine bands of Swyſſers away with them.</p>
                  <p>The king alſo by the Popes perſwaſion had ſent the Duke of Albanie from the ſiege of Pauia vvith 10000. footemen and 600. horſe to inuade the Realme of Naples, ſuppoſing to drawe the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialls thither for the defence of that Realme, vvhich notwithſtanding wiſely they forbare to do, knowing the Realme of Naples to be in ſufficient ſaftie if they ouerthrew the king.</p>
                  <p>Thus the kings camp being by the departure
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9751:37"/>
of thoſe aboue mentioned greatly weakened, and the forces that remayned with him, through the corruption of his officers not being the one halfe of the number that he payed, which was a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing that ſuch an abuſe ſhould be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Prince beeing with his armie in perſon himſelfe: the Imperialls being ignorant of none of theſe diſorders, determined to inuade him in his owne Campe, where through the defect of courage in the Swyſſers hee was taken priſoner, him ſelfe fighting more valiauntly then any man in his armie: many of the nobilitie were ſlayne and many taken, and the Swyſſers were in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all cut in pieces by the Landsknights, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of the auncient hatred betwene the ſayde Swyſſers and them.</p>
                  <p>This battaile is called the battaile of Pauia, and was fought vpon Saint Mathias day, being the day of the Emperours Natiuitie in the yeare 1525. according to the Italians but 1524. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the French, which variance ariſeth as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue mentioned becauſe the one beginne the yeare vpon the firſt of Januarie and the other not before Eaſter.</p>
                  <p>The Duke of Albanie after the kings captiuitie by the Popes meanes paſſed by ſea with his armie ſafly into Fraunce. Thus was this noble King through the diſorders principally proceding from his owne officers and Captaines taken priſoner as you haue heard, who not being diſmayed with this ſodaine
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9751:38"/>
blow of fortune, behaued himſelf with ſuch prince<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly magnanimitie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was honored &amp; had in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen of his enemies in ſuch ſort that his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie blemiſhed not, but rather cauſed his noble vertues the more to ſhine, as by this one example which I will rehearſe ſhall well appeare. So ſoone as hee was brought to his lodging hee ſent for the leaders of the Imperiall armie, and tould them that hee had a ſute vnto them which he truſted they would not denie him.</p>
                  <p>Wherevnto when they ſemed doubtfull what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to make, ſuppoſing it to bee ſome great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of difficultie that they mought not aduenture to graunt without the Emperours priuitie, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing their immagination, tould them it was no ſuch important ſuit that required any ſuch doubt, onely his deſire was that the young French boyes taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battel mought not remaine with the Italians, but in exchaunge of other priſoners bee deliuered to the Spaniards, which was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently graunted and executed accordingly, though not without great admiration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Imperialls, who wondered that the king forgetting his owne miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune being of a Prince made a priſoner in one day, could remember to bee ſo carefull of the chaſtitie of theſe young boyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:9751:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 8. <hi>The King of England confederateth himſelfe with the eſtate of Fraunce, and the Princes and ſtates of Italie themſelues againſt the Emperour. The Imperialls ſeaze vpon the Duchie of Milan. The King ſayleth into Spaine. The treatie of Madrid. The king is deliuered, The Children of Fraunce goe in hoſtage into Spaine.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg> The Emperour hauing receaued the <note place="margin">1525.</note> newes of the kings captiuitie, ſemed to take it very modeſtly, forbidding all ſignes of ioy to be vſed, &amp; alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that we ought to reioyce at the ouerthrow of Turkes and infidels but not of any Chriſtian Prince, which his modeſt behauiour put the world in great hope that hee would deliuer the king with ſuch honorable conditions as mought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a quiet peace in Chriſtendome &amp; perpetual amitie betweene them twayne. But his rigor to the king afterwards declared his ſpirit to be farre from any ſuch moderation as his externall beehauiour made ſhew of.</p>
                  <p>Farther you ſhall vnderſtand that the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receipt of theſe newes, leuied amighty armie purpoſing in perſon to inuade Fraunce, but hee continued not long in that minde vppon theſe occaſions folowing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:9751:39"/>
Firſt certaine difficulties aroſe betwene the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and him, the king demaunding, bearing but equall charges with the Emperour, an vnequall part of the conqueſt of Fraunce, and the Emperour hoping to obtaine better conditions of the King of Fraunce by making peace, then he ſhould doe if he ioyned with the king of England by making warre.</p>
                  <p>Secondarely the Cardinall of YORKE being altogether French, and enemie to the Emperour diſwaded the king of England from farther ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the Emperour, who was alredie ſo mightie, that his greatneſſe was become terrible to all his neighbours round about him.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly after the battaile of Pauia the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſemed not to make ſo great accompt of the king of England as before he had done, for firſt he refuſed to marie the Lady Mary the king of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands daughter being very young, and maried the ſiſter of <hi>Ihon</hi> king of Portugale, as hereafter you ſhall heare, with whom he receiued a great maſſe of money whereof he ſtood in great neede.</p>
                  <p>Farther whereas beefore the battaile of Paui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, he neuer wroat letter to the king of England but with his owne hand and with this ſubſcrption <hi>Your ſonne and Coſin Charles,</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battaile he neuer wroat letter with his owne hand nor with other ſubſcription then his ſimple name Charles, all the which reaſons cauſed the king of England by little and little to ſtraunge himſelfe from the Emperours
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9751:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
friendſhip. But the thing that moſt wrought the alteration of his minde was that the Lady Regent of Fraunce the kings mother ſent vnto him a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman with letters very humbly wrtiten, wherein ſhe ſignified vnto him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was not honorable for ſo noble a Prince as he was, to inuade a king bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Captiue, &amp; a Chriſtian Realme afflicted with the captiuitie of their Prince, which ſubmiſſion pearced ſo depely into the breaſt of this coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious king, that preſently he not onely diſmiſſed his armie which he had leuyed to his charge, not demaunding one penie in regarde thereof: but alſo from that day forward became the greateſt friend that the Realme of Fraunce had, and ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into league with the Regent for the deliuerie of the king hir ſonne, for the accompliſhment alſo whereof, the ſayd king of England ſo eareneſtly trauayled with all the ſtates of Chriſtendome, that in the ende he effected it, in ſuch ſort that ſo ſoone as king <hi>Francis</hi> had ſet foote in Fraunce, the firſt thing he dyd was, that preſently hee wroat a letter of thanckes to king Henry aduertiſing him of his libertie, for the which hee acknowledged himſelfe more beehoulding to him then to all the Princes of Chriſtendome beſides.</p>
                  <p>Such true nobilitie reigned in Princes being in hoſtilitie, at thoſe dayes, wheras now this age is ſo farr degenerated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the magnanimitie of their fathers, that one Prince ſeeketh to take away an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lyfe by treaſon, murther, poyſon and ſuch
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:9751:40"/>
like vilanous attempts, which the heathen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues deteſted and abhorred. But to returne to our Hiſtorie. The kings captiuitie aſtoniſhed not onely Fraunce but alſo all Italie, beecauſe all the Princes and ſtates thereof ſemed now wholy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon the Emperours clemencie, none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being able to ſtand vpon his owne ſtrength. The Pope eſpecially was not a litle grieued with this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, who notwithſtanding that for his preſent ſaftie hee made an accord with the Imperials as did alſo the Venetians: yet their hart was farr from it, as the ſequell wel declared: for ſecretly &amp; vnder hand they practiſed to make a league betweene the ſtate of Fraunce, the Pope, the Venetians, and the duke of Milan, againſt the Emperour, which confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the Imperialls hauing diſcouered, preſently ſeazed all the Duchie of Milan to the Emperours vſe, ſaue the Caſtell of Milan into the which the Duke put himſelfe and endured the ſiege, and the Caſtell of Cremona, both the which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Imperialls enuyroned with trenches on all ſides.</p>
                  <p>But this ſeazing of the ſayde Duchie cauſed the league to diſcouer it ſelfe ſooner then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would. The king to the ende he mought the ſooner recouer his libertie went into Spaine, hoping by preſent conference with the Emperour, the ſooner to compound all their controuerſies.</p>
                  <p>But the Emperours rigor was ſuch in rude hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, neuer once vouchſafing to come to ſee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9751:40"/>
him, and propounding ſuch vnreaſonable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the king without the ruine of his Realme could not accept: that the King fell into a moſt daungerous and almoſt deſperate diſeaſe for verie griefe of minde.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore the Emperour doubting to loſe the fruits of his victorie by the kings death, came &amp; viſited him, &amp; ſo in the end peace was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Madrid,</hi> the 14 of Februarie 1525. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the French, but after the Italians 1526. being iuſt a yeare lacking but 10. daies ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings captiutie. But you ſhall vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the conditions of this treatie were ſo vnreaſonable that (as it is reported) the King proteſted hee would not obſerue them, when he ſhould be returned into his Realme, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the articles for the reſtitution of <hi>Burgundy</hi> to the Emperour, and the releaſing of his ſoueraintie ouer Flaunders</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding for the performance of this treatie <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the kings Children were deliuered in hoſtage to the Emperour, and for far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continuance of amitie beetweene theſe two Princes it was agreed that the king ſhould marie <hi>Elenor</hi> the Emperours ſiſter, promiſed as before you haue heard to the Duke of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> but neuer with any meaning to performe it.</p>
                  <p>And thus was the King deliuered, with promiſe that if he would not performe the treatie, he ſhould returne priſoner into Spaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:9751:41"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>The Emperour marieth, Fraunce refuſeth the treatie of Madrid. The kings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates in Italie, beeſiege Milan twice, but in vayne. The Pope is twice taken priſoner by the Imperialls, Rome is ſacked. Bourbon is ſlayne at the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ault. The King of England and Fraunce defie the Emperour. The Pope is reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to libertie. Genoua returneth to the Kings obedience. The King inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Milan and the Realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but by reaſon of the reuoult of Andre D'oria to the Emperour, and the plague that entered into the French camp, his enterpriſe was ouerthrowne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bout the beginning of this yeare 1526. the Emperour hauing refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">1526.</note> the king of Englands daughter as beefore you haue heard, maried <hi>Iſabella</hi> Daughter of <hi>Emanuel</hi> and ſiſter to Ihon King of <hi>Portugale.</hi> The king being returned into his Realme complayned greatly of the Emperours great inhumanitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, and his vnprincely vſage of him, being farre different from the entertainment that <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third king of England gaue to king Ihon
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9751:41"/>
of Fraunce taken priſoner by the Prince of Wales at the battaile of <hi>Poicters.</hi> Farther hee aſſembled the eſtates of his Realme, who according to the Kings minde vtterly condempned the treatie of Madrid, as forced vppon a priſoner by violence and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the kings powre to performe, and thus was the treatie broken and the Emperour deluded, and ſo his owne councell tould him he ſhould be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings deliuerie, vnleſſe he altered ſome points of the treatie. Notwithſtanding the King offered him two millions of crownes for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of his children, and diuers other honorable conditions in conſideration of the articles for the reſtitution of Burgundie, and the releaſe of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraintie of Flaunders, which the Emperour vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reiected, charging the king with periurie, becauſe not performing the treatie, he returned not priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againe according to his promiſe. But the Pope voluntarely without intreatie had aſſoyled him of that oath.</p>
                  <p>The king perceuing the Emperours obſtinacie, renewed his league with the king of England, and farther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federated himſelfe in Italie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, the Venetians, the Duke of Milan and diuers other ſtates againſt the Emperour, who all ioyntly ſent vnto him for the deliuerie of the kings children, offering him verie honorable conditions in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof if he would accept of them, but finding him to ſtande ſtifly vppon the treatie of Madrid, and that hee would admit no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:9751:42"/>
they iointly began war vpon him &amp; inuaded his dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in Italic, &amp; came with their armie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Milan hoping to take it &amp; to deliuer the duke of Milan who held the Caſtle as yet, but they failed of their purpoſe, &amp; were conſtrained with diſhonor to leuie their ſiege notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their armie came twice to the reliefe of the ſaid caſtle of Milan, which the duke conſidering, deſpairing of ſuccours, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt ſtarued in the caſtle for victuals, he made a compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the duke of Bourbon gouernour of Milan for the Emperour, whereby he yelded the caſtle into his hands, and it was agreed that Coma being held by the Imperials ſhould be deliuered to the duke of Milan, &amp; that there he ſhould reſide till the Emperour had heard his iuſtification. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſent againſt the confederats a mightie armie vnder the leading of the ſaid duke of Bourbon, and ſought alſo to ſtir vp a rebellion againſt the Pope in Rome itſelfe by meanes of the <hi>Coulonnois,</hi> who by cunning toke him priſoner in the vatican, &amp; made him yelde to ſuch conditions of peace as pleaſed them, and conſtrayned him to abandon his league with the confederats and to enter into league with the Imperials, &amp; with theſe conditions he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But that notwithſtanding, the duke <note place="margin">1527.</note> of Bourbon whoſe armie wanting pay deſired no thing more then to be inriched with the ſpoile of Rome, marched directly againſt the citie, toke it, &amp; ſacked it though with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of his owne life. The <hi>Pope</hi> with many of his <hi>Cardinals</hi> was empriſoned in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:9751:42"/>
the caſtle of Saint Angelo, &amp; put to their raunſome, &amp; conſtrained to yeld to ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of peace as it pleaſed the Imperials to propound vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Emperour hearing theſe newes, ſemed in outward ſhew to ſorrow greatly for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes empriſonment, &amp; the ſacking of Rome, but the truth is he was glad of it at his very hart, which alſo well appeared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that notwithſtanding, he ceaſed not the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times &amp; triumphs that he had appointed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birth of his ſonne. But the king of Fraunce and England ſent their Ambaſſadors to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour demanding the Popes deliuerie. And being entered into a ſtraight league together by means of the Cardinall of <hi>Yorke,</hi> who came this yeare with wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful pomp to <hi>Amiens</hi> to the king, they both ſent their Heraults to defie the Emperour, &amp; farther the king gaue the Emperour the lie, &amp; ſent vnto him a cartell of defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, wherein he chalenged the combat of him. But the Emperour ſeeing ſo many Princes and ſtates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, reſtored the Pope to his libertie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time <hi>Genoua</hi> by meanes of <hi>Andre D'oria</hi> beeing then in ſeruice with the King retourned to the Kings obedience. Wherevppon foorth with <note place="margin">1528.</note> the king leuying a mightie armie, ſent it vnder the leading of <hi>Monſieur de Lautrech</hi> into <hi>Italie,</hi> which recouered diuers townes in the Duchie of Milan, and beſieged &amp; tooke <hi>Pauia,</hi> &amp; ſacked it in reuenge of the kings captiuitie, &amp; had ſo good ſucceſſe there that it is thought the French mought haue recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not onely Milan, but alſo the whole countrey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:9751:43"/>
But the Pope being ſet at libertie, eyther to be reuenged of the Emperour, or in hope to haue the Realme of Naples for himſelfe, according to the agrement in his confederacie with the King, perſwaded the king to withdraw his armie out of the Duchie of Milan where his affaires proſpered well, and to ſend Lautrech to inuade the ſayde Realme of Naples, which the king to gratefie the Pope was contented to doe. Lautrech recouered all the ſayde Realme ſaue Naples it ſelfe, which he alſo beſieged. But during that ſiege <hi>Anáre D'oria</hi> who with the French nauie held the towne enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſea, ſodainely left the king, and went to the Emperours ſeruice, by meanes whereof the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialls were maſters of the Sea which beefore the French commaunded.</p>
                  <p>Farther the ſayd <hi>D'oria</hi> reuolted Genoua alſo from the king, &amp; dyd much miſchiefe to the French by ſea. But their greateſt miſfortune, and the very ruine of this enterpriſe was the plague which ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the French camp, whereof Lautrech him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe dyed, and whereby his armie was ſo extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the ſiege was abandoned, and the French forced to retourne home hauing loſt all that they had before taken as well in the ſayde Realme as in the Duchie of Milan.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:9751:43"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>Peace is concluded at Cambray. The Children of Fraunce are deliuered, the King mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Emperours ſiſter. The Emperour is crowned, Florence is be ſieged and yelded to the Pope, Ferdinand is choſen king of Romaines.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT in the end peace was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded <note place="margin">1529.</note> betwene theſe princes at Cambray, for all parts were wearie of the warrs, and the kings children were reſtored vnto him for the ſumme of two mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of crownes, which were preſently to be payd in this ſort. Firſt the king was preſently to paye to the king of England for the Emperour 400000. crownes of debt which the Emperour heretofore had borowed of the ſayd King. Farther he was likewiſe to pay to the ſayd king of England for the Emperour 500000. crownes forfaited by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to the ſayd king, for refuſing to marie the La die Marie the king of Englands daughter, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the princeſſe of Portugale, vppon payment of the which ſummes the king was to redeme all the Emperours obligations out of the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands hands, and to deliuer them to the Emperour. Thirdly he was to redeme out of the ſayd king of Englands hands a Iewell engaged to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd kings
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9751:44"/>
father by the Archduc Philip father to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for 50000 crownes, being a flower deluce ſet with ſtones, which beecauſe it had beene a Iuell of Philip ſurnamed Le bon duke of <hi>Burgundie</hi> the Emperour made no ſmall accompt of, the reſt of the two millions was preſentlie to be payed to the Emperour himſelfe, &amp; theſe conditions being performed the Children of Fraunce to bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered otherwiſe not.</p>
                  <p>T The Emperours purpoſe in turning the king of Englands debt vpon the king was this. Firſt hee hoped that the king, his Realme being empoueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and conſumed with the long warrs that it had endured, ſhould not bee able to make preſent pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo huge a maſſe of money as was to bee payed, firſt to the Emperour himſelfe, and ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to the king of England, for the redeeming of the Emperours bonds and iuells out of his hands, without preſent payment whereof, he aſſured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that the king of England would not dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the foreſayde bondes and iuells, and by that meanes the children of Fraunce ſhould remayne his priſoners ſtill.</p>
                  <p>Neyther was hee out of hope that happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſome variance would ariſe beetweene theſe two kings about payment of the money, and ſo their friendſhip be diſſolued, which was the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall marke he ſhot at, and as alſo partly it fell out in the ende as heereafter you ſhall heare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:9751:44"/>
But the king of England perceauing the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours cunning, and not beeing ignorant of the poore eſtate the Realme of Fraunce was fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, hauing ſuſtained ſuch a continuall tempeſt of warres againſt ſo many mightie enemies, euer ſince the beeginning of the reigne of king LEVVIS the twelfth till this very time as by the courſe of this Hiſtorie aboue written you may eaſely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue of a noble and heroicall mynde, ſent Sir <hi>Francis Brian,</hi> with all the Emperours obligations and the ſaide Iuell to king Francis, willing him on his part to ſignifie vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, firſt for the 400000. crownes of debt dew vnto the ſayde king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land by the Emperour, the king his maſter would giue the King libertie to paye them in fiue yeares. The 500000. crownes forfayted to him by the Emperour for not marrying the Lady Mary the ſayde king of Englands Daughter hee would frankely giue him, and the flower de luce hee woulde lykewyſe giue to his Godſonne Henry Duke of ORLEANS the kings ſecond ſonne, and thus was the ſayde flower de luce and all the Emperours oblygations by the king of Englands commandement delyuered contrarie to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours expectation into the kings hands, and the ſayd Emperour ſatiſfied in all his demaunds, &amp; therevpon the kings children ſet at libertie, the article for the reſtitution of Burgundie releaſed, and the amitie betwene the two kings continew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:9751:45"/>
And the next yeare 1530. the king maried E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenor <note place="margin">1530.</note> the Emperours ſiſter, and the ſayde Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour receaued the crowne Imperiall of the Pope at Bolonia vpon Saint Mathias day being his birth day where the peace betwene the king &amp; him was ſworne anew.</p>
                  <p>All the ſtates of Italie were reconciled to the Emperour, <hi>Francis Sforce</hi> was reſtored to his duchie of Milan, and the Emperour was inueſted by the Pope of the Realme of Naples, who alſo at the Popes requeſt ſent an armie to beſiege Florence, beecauſe the Florentines during the time of the Popes empriſonment in the hands of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, had chaced all the houſe of Medices out of Florence and ſpoyled all their goods.</p>
                  <p>In this ſiege the Prince of Orenge generall of the Emperours armie was ſlaine. But the ſayd Citie was ſo diſtreſſed that in the end it yelded, &amp; was deliuered into the Popes hands, who puniſhed them with great ſeueritie, ſuppreſſed their liberties and cleane altered their ſtate.</p>
                  <p>This yeare alſo Ferdinand the Emperours bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was choſen King of Romaines, and the Realme of Fraunce for certaine yeares remayned in peace.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:9751:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> II. <hi>The Practiſes of the kings of Fraunce and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land againſt the Emperour. The Turke inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Hungarie. The Pope and the Emperour meete at Bolonia, and the Pope and the king at Marſeilles. Henry the kings ſonne marrieth the Popes niece. The King of England falleth from the Pope, Pope Clement dyeth, Paulus the third ſuccedeth. The Duke of VVirtemberg re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth his Duchie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithſtanding both the KINGS <note place="margin">1531.</note> minde &amp; likewiſe the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands were exulcerated againſt the Emperour, the one beecauſe he ſaw himſelfe diſpoſſed of the Duchie of Milan, the conqueſt whereof had beene ſo chargeable both to his predeceſſor and to him, &amp; the other becauſe the Emperour defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt him, the cauſe of his Aunt, wife to the ſaid king of England, &amp; diſſwaded the Pope from graunting any Bull of deuorce betweene him and the ſayde Lady, whom the king was deſirous to put away becauſe ſhe had beene firſt his brothers wyfe, and by the lawes of God could not bee lawfull wyfe to him.</p>
                  <p>But the king of Fraunce was ſo impouriſhed, and wearied with long warres, that he thought
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9751:46"/>
it not time to attempt aught againſt the Emperour as yet.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding he laboured to draw the Pope to his partie, by offering a mariage beetweene the ſecond ſonne of Fraunce &amp; Catherin niece to the ſayd Pope, which afterward alſo tooke effect. And not content therewith, hee ſought alſo to ſtirre vp the Turke againſt the Emperour, and farther both he and the king of England practiſed a conſedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with ſuch of the Princes of Germanie as they knew to be euell affected to him. In this yeare alſo the kings mother dyed, and the duchie of Britaine was incorporated to the crowne of Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1532. the Turke by the kings perſwaſion as the Emperour ſayde inuaded Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, &amp; hauing <note place="margin">1532.</note> ſpoyled and robbed all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey retourned ſodainely to Conſtantinople, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the expectation of the king of England and Fraunce, both the which hating the Emperour moſt deadly, met together about this time at Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyne, and after went both together to Calais, where they were agreed to haue proclaymed warr againſt the Emperour during the Turkes inuaſion of Hungarie.</p>
                  <p>But the Turkes ſodaine departure out of the ſayde Realme, and his retourne to Conſtantinople cauſed them to alter their mindes, and to deferre the warre till a more conuenient time.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding wiſely they gaue foorth, that their meeting was to conferre together how
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:9751:46"/>
to make reſiſtance againſt the Turck, &amp; the better to colour their pretence, they ſent Ambaſſadours to diuers Princes of Germanie, &amp; other potentates of chriſtendome, to perſwade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter into league with them againſt the ſayd Turck. But the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <note place="margin">1533.</note> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherſide not being ignorant of theſe their practiſes came into Italie, and the Pope and he met together at Bolonia, wher in outward demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were great ſignes of loue and amitie. But it well appeared that their harts were farre aſunder, for the Emperour obtained no thing of that he deſired.</p>
                  <p>For firſt he perſwaded the Pope to beſtow his niece Catherine of Medices vppon Francis Sforce Duke of Milan, and ſecondarelie that he would aſſemble a generall councell both the which were denied him, onely the Pope at the Emperours ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſollicitation, and becauſe he would not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcontent him, agreed to enter into league with the Emperour, with the king of Romains his brother, and the other potentates of Italie (all ſaue the Venetians who refuſed to be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſayd league) for the defence of their eſtates in Italie, and each man was rated what charges he ſhould beare in thoſe warrs.</p>
                  <p>But with what minde this league was made ſoone after well appeared, for the Emperour was no ſoner departed into Spaine, but the Pope &amp; the king met at <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> wher the mariage betwen the ſecond ſonne of Fraunce and the Popes niece was
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:9751:47"/>
accompliſhed, &amp; farther the king moued the Pope for the Bull of deuorce betwene the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and and his wife the Emperours Aunt, which had before bene graunted in the yeare 1529. and ſent into England to Cardinall Campegius, in whoſe hands it remained till the Pope for feare of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour commaunded it to be burned, and at this time alſo notwithſtanding the kings ſolicitation for the ſame reaſon it could not be obtained. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the king of England withdrew him ſelfe and <note place="margin">1534.</note> his Realme from the Popes obedience, and proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him ſelfe ſupreme head of the Church within his owne dominions.</p>
                  <p>Soone after this meeting the Pope dyed, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Farneſe ſucceded him by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Paule, the third. Farther the Duke of Wirtemberg ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto him the Lantzgraue of Heſſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings ſolicitation &amp; with his monie inuaded the Duchie of Wirtemberg, wherof the ſayd Duke had before bene diſpoſſeſſed by the king of Romaines, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered it little to the ſayd king of Romaines con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, who notwithſtanding fearing farther troubles in the abſence of his brother the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in Spaine, was forced to wink thereat.</p>
                  <p>This yeare alſo <hi>Solyman</hi> the great Turck was ouerthrowen and put to flight in Perſia by the <hi>Sophy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:9751:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 12. <hi>The Emperour winneth Tunis and Gouletta in Afric. The king eſtabliſheth legions of footemen in Fraunce. VVarres bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Emperour &amp; the King about Sauoy. The Emperour inuadeth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince with euill ſucceſſe. Naſſau beeſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Perona in vayne. The King inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Picardie and Artoys. The warrs of Picmont and Saluſſes, truce for three moneths.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Emperour being in peace with the king made a iourney into Africa <note place="margin">1535.</note> and conquered Thunis and Goulet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, and ſo victoriouſly returned into Italie. The king in the meane time eſtabliſhed diuers lawes for the good gouernement of his Realme, and withall made alſo great proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the warrs, for he leuyed in his Realme an army of 50000. footemen which were in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall pay, and were diuided into Legions after the auncient Romaine diſcipline, and theſe were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in a redineſſe to offend or defend as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion required. In the meane time dyed the Duke of Milan, and the whole country was yelded to the Emperour, who ſeeing the king in a readineſſe with ſo mightie an armie, and doubting that he would vppon a ſodaine inuade the ſayd Duchie of Milan, being vtterly vnfurniſhed at that time of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9751:48"/>
all things neceſſarie for defence: thought good to temporiſe with the king, and to entertaine him with communication of marriage beetweene the Daulphin and the princeſſe of Portugale daughter to Queene Elenor, and likewiſe betwene <hi>Monſieur de' Angouleſme</hi> the kings third ſonne &amp; the Princeſſe of Spaine the Emperours daughter, but notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this temporiſing, the hatred theſe two princes bare the one to the other could noe lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bee ſmothered, but brake out into a bluddie warre vppon this occaſion which I will now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe.</p>
                  <p>The king claymed the duchie of Sauoy as appertayning to him in the right of his mother, <note place="margin">1536.</note> for the which cauſe hee inuaded it with his armie and conquered the whole countrey. The duke was entered into league with the Emperour and prayed ayde of him, who ſent <hi>Anthonie Leua</hi> to his reliefe. But the Kings armie beeing firſt in a readineſſe chaſed the Sauoyan cleane out of his Countrey before the Emperours ayde could come vnto him.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour came to Rome where in the conſiſtorie, hee made a moſt bitter inuectiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king, wherevnto the King anſwered by writing at large. Farther the ſayde Emperour ſeeing his confederate the Duke of Sauoy thus <note place="margin">1537.</note> ſpoyled of his countrey, in a great fury entered with a mightie armie into Prouince, perſwading himſelfe ſoone to be Lord of all Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>But after hee had remayned in Prouince a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:9751:48"/>
while, and ſaw the preparation that the king made againſt him, his armie alſo being in great penurie and diſtreſſe, becauſe the king had ſo ſtopped all the paſſages that no victuals could come to his campe, he ſoone returned into ſtalie without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing worthie of remembraunce, finding the Realme of Fraunce a morſell not ſo eaſie to be ſwalowed v<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as he imagined, on the other ſide the Earle of Naſſau at the ſame time inuaded Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardie and beſieged Perone, but after he had lyen two moneths before the towne, he was forced to leauie his ſiege and depart, the ſelfe ſame day that the Emperour retired out of Prouince.</p>
                  <p>Then the King on the other ſide inuaded the Emperours dominions in Picardie and Artoys, where hee ſpoyled many townes and villages, and tooke Heſdin both towne and caſtell, and lykewiſe Saint Pol which he ſtrongly fortefied. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the armie Imperiall vnder the leading of the Earle of Buren, ſoone after recouered Saint Pol, and entered into Fraunce, and tooke Montreuil and ſpoyled many other townes, and there truce was concluded beetweene theſe two Princes dominions onely in thoſe parts, for tenne monethes.</p>
                  <p>But the warres in Piemont endured ſtill, for you ſhall vnderſtand that about this tyme Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Marques of Saluſſes moſt trayterouſly and without any occaſion left the King and went to the Emperours ſeruice, for the which cauſe the kings
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:9751:49"/>
armie in Piemont entered into the ſayde Marqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate and before any ayde could come to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques from the Imperials, ſeazed all the countrey into the kings hands.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding ſoone after the armie Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall <note place="margin">1538.</note> vnder the leading of the Marques du Guaſt recouered in manner the whole countrey againe, and reſtored it to the ſayde Marques, all ſaue the caſtels of <hi>Verculo</hi> &amp; <hi>Carmagnolla,</hi> the later alſo wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they went and beſieged, &amp; there the ſayde Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques oſ Saluſſes was ſlaine with a musket ſhot.</p>
                  <p>But notwithſtanding that accident, the Marques of Guaſt toke the ſaide Caſtell of <hi>Carmagnolla,</hi> and entered into Piemont where hee recouered many places, which the King ſeeing, ſent a mightie armie into Piemont vnder the leading of Henry the Daulphin his ſonne, who preſented battayle to the ſayde Marques of Guaſt, which hee beeing farre inſeriour in forces refuſed.</p>
                  <p>The Daulphin recouered in a manner all the places that the ſayde Marques had before ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The king alſo himſelfe paſſed in perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Piemont. Wherevpon by the mediation of the Queene of Hungarie the Emperours ſiſter a generall truce was concluded for three moneths as well for theſe parts as beefore it had beene for Picardie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:9751:49"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>The Pope, the Emperour, and the king, mete at Nice in Prouince, a truce is there concluded for tenne yeares. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the King meete at Aigueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortes. The Empreſſe dyeth. Gaunt rebelleth. The Emperour paſſeth through Fraunce and repreſſeth the rebellion of Gaunt. The Kings Ambaſſadors are ſlayne. The Emperours vnfortunate voyage to Argier. The Turke iuuadeth Hungarie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT the Pope ſeeing the miſerable ſtate Chriſtendome was brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, through the continuall warrs of theſe two great Princes, trauayled all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee could to eſtabliſh a firme peace betwene them, wherefore he intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them both to meete him at Nice in Prouince.</p>
                  <p>Wherevnto they both condeſcended, and accordingly in Iune they all three met at the ſayde place of Nice, where the Pope endeuoured to make a finall peace betweene them, but when hee perceiued that could by no meanes bee brought to paſſe, hee concluded a truce for tenne yeares, which beeing done they all departed, the Pope to goe to Rome, the Emperour into Spaine, and the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:9751:50"/>
king by Auignion to retourne into Fraunce. But ſo ſoone as the king was arriued at Auignion, hee receaued newes that the Emperour beeing at Villa Francha, would gladly againe ſpeake with him, and that if it pleaſed him to come to Aigueſmortes he would there meete him. The king ſent the Queene to Villa Francha to viſit hir brother the Emperor, and himſelfe folowed after to Aigueſmortes, wher the Emperour came on land, and dyned with the King, and lodged with him all night in great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of loue and fraternitie. Afterward alſo the king went with the Emperour into his galey, where they were together a long time, &amp; ſo in great amitie departed the Emperour into Spaine and the king home.</p>
                  <p>In the yeare 1539. dyed the Empreſſe, and the towne of Gaunt rebelled againſt the Emperour, &amp; ſent <note place="margin">1539.</note> to ſubmit themſelues to the king, who not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly refuſed them, but alſo aduertiſed the Emperour thereof, who meaning in perſon to ſuppreſſe their rebellion, and knowing the iourney by ſea to bee long, and dangerous, becauſe tempeſt mought caſt him vpon the coaſt of England, (the king whereof was his enemie) as it had done his father in times paſt: ſent to the king, deſiring him that he mought paſſe the next way through France, promiſing him the reſtitution of Milan for one of his ſonnes, but hee beſought him not to demaund any aſſuraunce thereof in writing, till hee ſhould be come into the low countreys, leaſt hee ſhould ſeeme to yeeld the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:9751:50"/>
ſaide duchie not of his owne accord, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to obtaine his paſſage through Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>The king agreed to all his demaunds, &amp; receaued him into his realme, and conueighed him through it into his owne dominions with all the honor that poſſibly mought be imagined. But after he was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme of France, firſt he began to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſe about the reſtitution of the ſaid Duchie of Milan till hee had ſpoken with his brother the king of Romaines, and afterwards flatly denied that he had made any ſuch promiſe at all, and thus was the king deluded, agreable whereunto certaine words much vſed by the Emperour in his paſſage through France, wer better vnderſtod after his ſaid paſſage by the ſequell that folowed, than whan they were vttered, for you ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Monſieur de Sanſſac</hi> was appointed to attend vpon him with all ſorts of Haukes, wherein the ſaide Emperour ſemed to take great delight, eſpecially with flying at the Kight, which the French call <hi>Voler le Milan,</hi> in ſo much that he vſed often to aſke the ſaid <hi>Sanſſac</hi> whether they ſhould <hi>Voler le Milan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which after his departure out of Fraunce and his deluding of the king for the reſtitution of the Duchie of Milan, was interpreted not to be ment of flying at the Kight, but as a ieaſt the Emperour in his owne conceit made at the Kings ſimplicitie, in beeleeuing that for his paſſage through Fraunce he would reſtore the ſaid Duchie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:9751:51"/>
The ſaid Emperour vnder colour and promiſe of pardoning the <hi>Gantoys</hi> all their offences entered <note place="margin">1540.</note> with his armie into Gaunt, where he made a blud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and cruell execution of all the offendors, tooke away their weapons, ſeazed all their priuiledges, &amp; built a Caſtle of the Abby of Saint Bauon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the towne &amp; hould it in awe in the nature of a citadelle. This diſſimulation of the Emperours aboue mentioned touching the reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Milan ſo faithfully promiſed, gaue the king iuſt cauſe to be ielous of all his actions, and to fortefie himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with as many friends as he could make, wherfore he ſent <hi>Caeſar Fregoſe</hi> &amp; <hi>Ricon</hi> his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors the one to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other to negotiate <note place="margin">1541.</note> with the Turke, who paſſing peacably through the dominions of the Emperor as the kings good bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, friend and confederate, were both ſlaine vpon the Riuer of Poe by the Marques of <hi>Guaſt,</hi> and that by the Emperours commaundement as the King ſayde, whoſe meaning was to haue found their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions about them, and ſo to haue diſcouered all the kings ſecrets. But the ſaid Ambaſſadors for the better aſſurance, had ſent their packets an other way to Venis, &amp; ſo the ſaid Marques fayled of his purpoſe. The king demaunded iuſtice at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours hands for this wicked fact, naming vnto him the men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had committed this vilanous murther, &amp; directly prouing the ſayde Marques to haue beene author thereof. But becauſe the Emperour refuſed to doe iuſtice heerin, as reaſon was he ſhould haue
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:9751:51"/>
done, it is manifeſt that the fact was not commited but by his commaundement. In this yeare alſo the Emperor made his iourney by ſea into <hi>Africk</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to beſiege <hi>Argier</hi> but his nauie was ſo toſſed with tempeſt, that with great daunger of his perſon, and infinit loſſe both of treaſure, munition, ſhips, &amp; men, he was forced to returne home. But it had ben much more honorable for him to haue gone to aide his brother, whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Turke</hi> ſpoiled at this very time of the greateſt part of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> then to haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted this voiage into <hi>Africk,</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Emperour to procede of couardiſe, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that becauſe he durſt not goe againſt the Turke who was in perſon in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> he choſe the other enterpriſe as eaſier and of leſſe daunger: But to proceede.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Warrs renewed betwene the Emperour and the king. The king inuadeth the Emperour with foure armies. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour inuadeth the Duke of Cleues. The king winneth Landerſey, inuadeth Luxembourg the ſecond time. The Emperor ioyned with the king of England, be ſieged Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſey, but in vaine. The cauſes why the king of England left the kings friendſhip.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe king ſeing the Emperour returned from his voiage in <hi>Africk,</hi> (during the which like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince he forbare to attempt any warre againſt him) ſolicited him earneſtly to doe iuſtice for the murther of his two Ambaſſadors, and farther ſent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:9751:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to Marie Queene of Hungarie the Emperours ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter &amp; regent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> low countries to haue the towne of S. Pol deliuered to him according to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the late truce concluded betwene the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and him. But receauing vppon both theſe points an anſwer that liked him not, he determined to recouer by warr that which he could not obtain by reaſon. Wherefore he inuaded the Emperours <note place="margin">1542.</note> dominions with foure ſeuerall armies. Firſt he ſent one armie vnder the leading of the Daulphin his ſonne to beſiege Perpignian in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of Rouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilion in Spaine, ſuppoſing the towne to be worſe prouided for defence than in deede it was, and this armie did him no ſeruice, but was forced to returne home &amp; relinquiſh the enterpriſe. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d armie vnder the leading of the Duke of Orlea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the kings ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſonne, inuaded the Duchie of Luxembourg, &amp; toke almoſt all the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g places therof, euen Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourg it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Farther during the aboad of the Kings armie before Luxembourg, certaine bands were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the Duke of Longueuille and Martin van Roſſam, who met with the prince of Orenge comming to relieue the ſaid town of Luxembourg and ouerthrew him, and purſued him euen to And<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe gates, the ſuburbes alſo whereof they toke &amp; ſpoiled &amp; burned them, but the towne they could <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot take, wherefore they returned to the Duke of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> lying ſtill at the ſiege of Luxembourg, and ioyned themſelues with him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:9751:52"/>
But Luxembourg being taken the king reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued home his ſonne, whoſe back was no ſoner turned, but the Imperialls preſently recouered all the ſayd Duchie from the French.</p>
                  <p>The third armie vnder the leading of the Duke of Vendoſme inuaded Artoys and ſpoiled all the countrie, and toke diuers ſmall places, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, the ſayd Duke lodged his armie all the winter in the garriſon townes. The fourth armie was ſent into Piemont with a purpoſe to haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the Duchie of Milan. But the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour had prouided well for the defence thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that to ſtay the French from attempting aught againſt the ſayd Duchie of Milan, the Marques of Guaſt was ſent into Piemont to make head againſt the French, where betwene him and Monſieur de Langey generall of the French forces, who dyed during theſe warrs, and afterward betwene him and the Marſhall'd Annebault many feats of armes but no great exploit was done, &amp; thus theſe foure armies ſtode the king in an exceſſiue charge and turned him neither to honor nor profit. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the armie that was in Picardie vnder the leading of the Duke of Vendoſme, winter being paſt, put it ſelfe againe into the field and toke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places in Artoys, and namely Lilliers a little <note place="margin">1543.</note> but a ſtrong towne &amp; likewiſe Bapaulme, &amp; burned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, finding almoſt no reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rey, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour had withdrawen all his forces
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:9751:53"/>
out of the ſtrong places, and ſent for them to ayde him againſt the Duke of Cleues, vppon whom hee made warre, and whoſe countrey hee conquered and ſubdewed at this preſent.</p>
                  <p>But the King in the meane time to withdraw the Emperour from inuading the ſayde Duke of Cleues being the kings confederate, entered with a mightie armie into the Emperours dominions &amp; tooke <hi>Landerſey</hi> and fortefied it, and afterward alſo ſent the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> againe to inuade the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie of <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> who wan diuers townes in that Countrey and namely recouered <hi>Luxembourg</hi> it ſelfe, which was now the ſecond tyme taken by the French.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour on the other ſide being ayded by the king of England beſieged <hi>Landerſey</hi> fortefied by the French as you haue heard, whether the King came in perſon with a mightie armie to relieue the towne, in ſuch ſort that the two armies ioyned ſo nere together that the battell was aſſuredly looked for.</p>
                  <p>But the king hauing ſufficiently victualed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued the towne which was the onely cauſe of his comming, retired ſafly with his armie into France, and the Emperour ſoone after, for want of victuals, and becauſe of the continuall raine that fell, &amp; the winter that approched, about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth or eighth of Nouember leuyed his ſiege. A man may mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle heere how it ſhoule come to paſſe that the King of England, betwene whom and the King had
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:9751:53"/>
bene ſo ſtraight a league, and from whom ſo many curteſies had proceded towards the king and his Realme in their moſt troubles and greateſt aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſhould now become his foe and ioyne with the Emperour (whom hee had ſo deadly hated) in the inuaſion of the kings dominions.</p>
                  <p>But you ſhal vnderſtand that this proceded partly of the king of Englands owne diſpoſition, partly through the kings fault, and partly through the Emperours cunning. Firſt as touching the King of England, trew it is that as himſelfe was a Prince of a noble and a franck minde and one that would endeuour to pleaſure his friend to his vttermoſt power: ſo if himſelfe likewiſe were not ſatiſfied in all his demaunds at his friends hands, hee was by nature apte to ſtrange himſelfe from his friend, not alwayes ſo depely conſidering as was requiſit his friends abilitie to accompliſh that which hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe hee had ſhewed himſelfe a firme, yea almoſt an onely friend to the realme of France during the time of the kings captiuitie, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at the deliuerie of the Children of Fraunce as before mention is made, he toke it very vnkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the kings hand. Firſt that hee payed not his money dew vnto him, for the which he had giuen the king fiue yeares day of payment, and the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof the Emperour had turned ouer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the king of purpoſe to ſet theſe two Princes at variance as before you haue heard.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:9751:54"/>
Secondarely he was grieued that the king obtained not for him the Bull of deuorce at the Popes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, which he was perſwaded the king by his authoritie mought haue procured, if he had delt ſo earneſtly in that buſineſſe as friendſhip required y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould. Now as touching the king he fayled towards the king of England in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt point that is the payment of his monie, through want of abilitie, for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror held him in ſuch continuall wars, that he was forced to leauie extreamly of his ſubiects, &amp; neuer could be in caſe to pay debts, &amp; as touching the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point namely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bull of deuorce, trew it is that the king after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſtitution of his children trauailed not ſo earneſtly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſines as before he had done, either becauſe he held ſomwhat of the diſpoſition of his countrey men, <hi>who are ſaide to remember good turnes no longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be in doing,</hi> or becauſe he was loth to offend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour, with whom he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded peace &amp; whoſe ſiſter he had maried, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope obſtinate, or a feard to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the Bull in reſpect of the Emperors greatnes in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, or laſtly becauſe he held the caſe deſperate, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the king of Englands reuolt from the Pope. Whether any of theſe reaſons, or all of them, or ſome other vnknowne to vs cauſed him to deale cowldly in the king of Englands buſineſſe we can but deuine, but certaine it is that the kings remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this cauſe mightely grieued the King of England, and diminiſhed a great part of his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the king.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:9751:54"/>
Laſtly as touching the Emperour, hee vſed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding cunning to ſeuer theſe two Princes, whoſe amitie hee ſaw to bee the countermine of all his practiſes and procedings.</p>
                  <p>For firſt hee turned ouer his owne debt to the king of England, vpon the king of Fraunce, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to caſt a boane betweene them to ſet them at variance as before you haue heard: Farther ſo ſoone as he perceued the king of Englands minde to bee a little alienated from the king, hee fayled not to doe his endeuour to aggrauate euerie ſmall vnkindeneſſe, and to make a mountaine of euerie moulehill.</p>
                  <p>Beeſides this hee wroate paſſing kinde letters to the king of England, deſiring him to remember the oulde friendſhip that had euer beene betwene the houſe of Burgundie and the Realme of England, and likewiſe not to forget the auncient enmitie and the many quarells that were yet depending bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene England and Fraunce, adding that if any vnkindeneſſe had paſſed betweene them two in regard of his Aunts cauſe, it was now cleane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten on his part by his Aunts death, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting farther vnto him, that if hee the ſayde Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour would embrace the king of France his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: the king offered to enter into league with him, and to abandon his league with the ſayd king of England, or any other prince in Chriſtendome that the ſayde Emperour ſhould miſlike of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:9751:55"/>
And at ſuch times as the Emperour had theſe purpoſes in his head, hee would in apparance make ſo much of the king of Fraunce, and haue ſuch conference with him and his Ambaſſadors, and ſeeme ſo wholy in all matters to depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his direction and aduiſe, that hee made not onely the king of England, but all the kings other confederats in Chriſtendome to doubt that he ment to doe as the Emperours letters reported, namely to enter into league with him, and to forſake all his other friends, and thus vnderhand the Emperour made the king himſelfe the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to cut his owne throat, and to ſeuer from him all his friends.</p>
                  <p>Whervnto I alſo adde that to draw the king of England to his partie &amp; to ioyne armes with him, he offered him of the conqueſt of Fraunce what portion he would deſire himſelfe, and by theſe meanes was the King of England wonne from the Kings friendſhip, and ſent a Herrault to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the King, and preſently paſſed ouer his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ioyne with the Emperour before Landercy as alreadie you haue heard. But to returne to the matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:9751:55"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. <hi>The Turke ioyned with the kings forces, take Nice in Prouince, the Emperour entereth into Cambray. Furſtembergs ſucceſſe in the duchie of Luxembourg. The Engliſh ſpoyle the Countrey of Bouloynoys. The warres in Piemont, and the battayle of Serizoles. The Emperour recouereth Luxembourg, hee and the King of England inuade Fraunce. The King of England win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Boloyn, peace betwene all theſe Princes. The death of the Kings of England and Fraunce.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He King ſeeing him ſelfe thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded by the Emperour and the King of England, was forced to pray in ayde of the Turke, who ſent his nauie to ioyne with the Kings in the ſiege of Nice in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and the towne they tooke &amp; therein exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted great crueltie, but the Caſtle they could not take, wherefore they retired themſelues.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour on the other ſide by cunning entered into the towne of Cambray, and in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance left them in their auncient libertie, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſo brideled them, by a citadelle which he
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:9751:56"/>
cauſed the Citizens the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues at their owne charge to build, and into the which he put a gariſon of his owne ſouldiours, that he brought them to plaine ſlauerie and bondage. Farther the ſayd Emperour ſent alſo Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eatle of Furſtemberg with an army to recouer Luxembourg, who recouered diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces in the countrey, &amp; went and layed his ſiege be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Luxembourg it ſelfe, but hearing of the prince of Melphes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to ſuccour the towne, he leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſiege &amp; retired into Allemayne, &amp; the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch recouered all the places that before they had loſt. But the Engliſh on the other ſide ſpoiled and forra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all the countrey of Boulonoys. The king ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuccoured Luxembourg, ſent an army into Pie mont vnder the leading of the Earle of Anghien a moſt valiant yong prince, who wan diuers townes there &amp; in the Marquiſat of Saluſſes from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of Guaſt generall of the Emperours forces, &amp; went and beſieged Carignan, whether the ſaid Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ques <note place="margin">1544.</note> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> army Imperiall came to leuie the ſiege, but the French at a place called Serizoles, gaue him battaile and ouerthrew him, &amp; ſlew 7000. of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and tooke 2000 priſoners. After the which bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile the ſaid Monſieur d'Anghien toke Carignan and diuers other townes in Piemont &amp; in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſat of Montferrat. But on the other ſide the Emperour with a huge armie inuaded the Duchie of Luxembourg, and recouered Luxembourg the chiefe Citie thereof, and diuers other townes, and namely S. Diſier, which laſt was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:9751:56"/>
&amp; long defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it ſelfe againſt the Imperial armie. This yeare alſo the Emperour &amp; the king of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federated together, inuaded France with ſo great forces, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is reported aboue 80000. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue ben in both their armies. Their purpoſe was to haue ſacked Paris, as vndoubtedly they had done, if the king of England had marched for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward according to his promis to the Emperour, &amp; had not ſtayed at the ſiege of Bouloyne, by meanes whereof the Emperour ſeeing his armie to be in diſtreſſe of victualls, &amp; that the Engliſh armie mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not forward to his ſuccour according to their agrement, concluded peace with the king and reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his forces out of Fraunce. In the meane time the king of England wan Boloyne which was yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him by Monſieur de Veruins the fourth of September, which being done the king of England returned home and landed at Douer the firſt of October.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the next yeare after many ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes and feates of armes done betwen the french <note place="margin">1545.</note> and Engliſh as well by ſea as land, peace was trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted off betwene theſe two Kings, and in the ende after many difficulties concluded, but not proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before Whitſonday being the thirtenth of Iune 1546. &amp; thus God miraculouſly preſerued the Realme of Fraunce, which vndoubtedly had ſtood in great daunger, if God had not put into the king of Englands head to ſtay at the ſiege of Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie and not to march forward to ioyne with the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:9751:57"/>
Emperour as hee ought to haue done, which his error in all apparance was the preſeruation of the Realme of Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour hauing made peace with the king entered into warre againſt the Proteſtants of <note place="margin">1546.</note> Germanie, and both he &amp; they ſent to king Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for ayde, but he refuſed to giue ayde to ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, promiſing to be an indifferent friend to both.</p>
                  <p>The eight and twenteth of Ianuarie folowing died Henry king of England, which newes the king tooke grieuouſly when he heard it, as well becauſe of the great good will that had been betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as alſo becauſe the king was in hope to haue made a firme league with him, &amp; laſtly becauſe they two hauing beene almoſt of one yeares and of one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, he foreſaw his owne ende to draw neere. Notwithſtanding after the ſayd king of Englands death, he renewed the league lately made betwene them twaine, with king Edward king Henryes ſon, and not long after dyed alſo himſelfe at Rambollet the laſt day of March in the yeare 1546. after the French accompt, who begin not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare till Eaſter, hauing liued 53. yeares &amp; reigned two and thirtie and three moneths, and ſixe dayes.</p>
                  <p>This was a Prince endued with many excellent parts, eſpecially magnanimitie, curteſie and libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and farther ſo great a patron, louer, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncer of learning, that he may iuſtly be called the father &amp; ſounder of good letters. What his fortune
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:9751:57"/>
was in this world may eaſely be gathered out of his Hiſtorie, wherin it doth appeare that ſhe was more froward then fauourable vnto him, but one great grace of God he had, that no aduerſitie was able to diminiſh the magnanimitie of his minde, beſides that he was of an excellent memorie and exceding eloquent in his owne tongue.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>HENRY THE SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of that name King of Fraunce.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>King Henry commeth to the Crowne, The Emperours warres in Germanie. The Engliſh inuade Scotland. The rebellion of Guyenne.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O King Francis the firſt ſucceded his onely ſonne Henry the ſecond being eight &amp; twentie yeares of age, in the very beginning of whoſe reigne the Emperour (as before you haue heard in the ende of king Francis his reigne) was entered into a warre in Germanie againſt the Proteſtants <note place="margin">1547.</note>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:9751:58"/>
namely the Duke of Saxonie, and the Lantzgraue of Heſſen, and diuers other Princes and townes confederated with them againſt him, perſwading the Pope (who ſent him ayde in theſe warrs) that his quarel was Religion, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princes Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Germanie, many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which were in his Camp &amp; ayded him, he pretended that he made warr vppon them for their rebellion, although in truth neither of both theſe were the cauſe motife of this warre, but his owne ambition, for his purpoſe was by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Germanies help againſt the Germaines, ſo to weaken both parts, and in the meane time ſo to plant garriſons of Spaniards in the ſtrong places of the countrey, that in the ende he mought make the eaſier conqueſt of the whole. And ſuch ſucceſſe he had at the beginning of theſe warrs, that he toke the Duke of Saxonie priſoner, &amp; made the Lantz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue come &amp; yeld him ſelfe to his mercie, but with this condition that he ſhould not be detained in priſon, which article the Emperour ſo gloaſed with a Spaniſh expoſition, that, that notwithſtanding he empriſoned him, alleadging that the article menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned onely perpetual empriſonment. The Palfz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue alſo and the Duke of Wirtemberg and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other Princes and free Townes ſubmitted them ſelues to him and with their money bought their peace.</p>
                  <p>You haue heard before how Henry the eight king of England dyed a little before king Francis, and left behinde him Prince Edward his ſonne, a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:9751:58"/>
childe about tenne yeares of age, the ſayed King Henry before his death had practiſed a marriage in Scotland betwene the ſayd prince his ſonne after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward called Edward the vj<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the heyre of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land being about foure yeares of age, and ſo farre this matter was proceded in, that the greateſt part of the ſtates of Scotland had giuen their conſent thereunto, but after king Henrys death, by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the Queene mother being of the houſe of Guyſe, and by the practiſe of the French faction (who could not endure this vniting of theſe two Realmes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd mariage) the treatie made with king Henry was diſauowed, and a practiſe ſet on foote to beſtow this yong Princes vpon the Daul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin of Fraunce, for the which cauſe, the Engliſh men entered into Scotland with a mightie armie, &amp; ſpoiled all the countrie, whom the Scotts encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering with all their forces at a place called Muſcle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borow, were ouerthrowen and a great number of them ſlayne, in September this yeare 1547. after the which victorie the Engliſh men tooke manie Caſtles and ſtrong places, and entered as farre as Edemborough the chiefe Citie of the Countrey, and fortified Hedington a ſtrong Towne, where what happened &amp; what iſſue theſe warres had, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after you ſhall heare.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour hauing ended his warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned in Germanie, and eſtabliſhed the <note place="margin">1548.</note> 
                     <hi>Interim</hi> which was a forme of Religion to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued till the aſſemblie of a generall counſell came
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:9751:59"/>
downe into the low countries, leading the Duke of Saxonie and the Lantzgraue with him as it were in triumph, to the no ſmall griefe of diuers Princes of the Empire, eſpecially of Duke MAVRICH ſonne in law to the ſayde Lantzgraue, as the ſequell ſhall well declare. About this tyme alſo the Prince of Spaine the Emperours ſonne came out of Spaine into Italie, and from thence to Bruxelles to his father beeing honorably receaued in all places through which he paſſed.</p>
                  <p>But the Realme of Fraunce beeing deliuered from forrayne warres, beeganne to bee vexed with domeſticall ſeditions, for a great rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was rayſed at BOVRDEAVX and through all GVIENNE and XAINTOIGNE, for a newe impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition increaſed vppon Sault, for the appeaſing whereof the Conſtable and Monſieur d'Aumal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le were ſent into thoſe partes, who puniſhed very ſharply them of BOVRDEAVX becauſe they had ſlaine the kings officers and commited many diſorders, and tooke from them all their priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and condemned both them and other townes that had offended in great ſummes of money, and ſo appeaſed the tumult.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:9751:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>The King aydeth the Scots againſt the Engliſh, hee inuadeth the Countrey of Boulonoys. The Queene of Scots is cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Fraunce. Paule the third dyeth. Iulius the third ſuccedeth, peace betwene England and Fraunce.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue heard how the laſt yeare the Engliſh men were entered into Scotland, as farre as <hi>Edingbourg</hi> and had ouerthrowen the Scots at Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcleborow, for the which cauſe the Scots ſent into Fraunce for ayde, and the King knowing how preiudiciall it ſhould bee for him and his Realme to ſuffer the Engliſh men to neſtle in Scotland, ſent thether an armie of 6000. men vnder the leading of <hi>Monſieur d'Eſſe, Strozzi,</hi> the <hi>Rhingraue,</hi> and others, who made head againſt the Engliſh men and much endamaged them, &amp; wanne Hedington which they had fortefied from them, while in the meane time their nauie conueighed the young Queene into Fraunce, notwithſtanding the Engliſh nauie that lay vpon the Sea to ſtoppe their paſſage, purpoſly to haue ſurpriſed the ſayde young Queene and to haue brought hir into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but the French nauie eſcaped them and ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſafly in Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:9751:60"/>
After the conueighing away of the young Queene the king reuoqued d'Eſſe, and ſent de Thermes a valiant ſouldier and a wiſe man to take the charge of his armie in Scotland, willing him to buſie the Engliſh men on that ſide, while the French forces entered into the Countrey of Boulonoys, for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that peace had beene concluded (as before you haue heard) betwene king Francis and king Henry before their death, and afterward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed alſo betwene the two Realmes: yet that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the French perceauing the Realme of England to be vexed with ſeditions becauſe of the alteration of Religion: vſed that opportunitie, and beſieged Bouloyne but could not take it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding diuers other ſmall peces held by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in the countrey of Boulonoys namely Boulon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, Hambletow, and Montlambert, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they toke. This yeare alſo the tenth of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber died Pope Paule the third, to whom after three moneths diſſencion in the Conſiſtorie ſucceded Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius the third, and this yeare alſo in December died Margaret Queene of Nauarra ſiſter to king Francis, a Lady of an excelent ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>But after theſe wars aboue mentioned had thus paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as you haue hard ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning of this kings <note place="margin">1550.</note> reigne betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French &amp; Engliſh nations as well in Scotland as in Boulonoys: both parts diſpoſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to peace. England was afflicted not onely with ſorraine warrs, but alſo with domeſticall ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the commons, and diſſentions among the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:9751:60"/>
nobles, &amp; the French king was entered into practiſe againſt the Emperour, both in Italie with Octauio Prince of Parma, and in Germanie with duke Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and diuers other Princes, who hated the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour deadly for his extreame tiranie vſed againſt the liberties of their country. Wherefore the King meaning to attempt ſomewhat againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was the more inclined to make peace with England, thereby to haue all cleere on that ſide of Fraunce. Both the Realmes therfore being thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to concord, their commiſſioners met &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded peace with theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions. Boloyne was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the French, for the which they payed to the king of England 400000. crownes. The king of England promiſed to marie Elizabeth the eldeſt daughter of Fraunce, afterward wife to Philip king of Spaine. Both Engliſh and French departed Scotland which was ordained to be gouerned by one of their owne nation, and both the Kings were made knights each of others order.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 3. <hi>The warres of Parma and Mirandula. The kings nauie ſpoyleth diuers Holandiſh ſhippes. The Turke winneth Tripoli.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe king hauing thus eſtabliſhed peace on that ſide of his realme began to attend to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine practiſes againſt the Emperor as well in Italie as in Germanie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:9751:61"/>
The firſt attempt that he made againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was the warre of Parma in Italie, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <note place="margin">1551.</note> vpon this occaſion: Petrus Aloiſius Franeſius ſonne to Pope Paule the third had giuen him by his father with the conſent of the conſiſtorie of Cardinalls Parma and Placencia in exchaunge of other lands, and was created Duke thereof.</p>
                  <p>This Peter the tenth of September in the yeare 1547. was ſlaine in his owne houſe not without the conſent of Ferdinando Gonzaga gouernour of Milan for the Emperour as it was thought. For preſently vpon his death the ſaid Ferdinando came to Placencia, and entered into it, and placed a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon in it to the Emperours vſe, and farther alowed Giouanni Aguzzolo who killed the ſayde Peter, with his owne hands, twentie ſouldiours for his guard. Octauius Peters ſonne and ſonne in law to the Emperour (for he had married the Emperours baſe daughter widow of Alexander Medices duke of Florence) demaunded of the Emperour againſt Gonzaga iuſtice of his fathers death, and that Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia mought bee reſtored to him againe, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him no thing but delatorie anſwers, &amp; fearing to be ſpoiled of Parma as alreadie he was of Placentia: hee ſought for ſuccour at the hands of Iulius tertius newly choſen Pope, who miſliking the Emperours greatnes in Italie, perſwaded Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius to put himſelf vnder the protection of France, not ſo much regarding Octauius good thereby
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:9751:61"/>
as hoping by this meanes to ſet theſe two Princes at variaunce, which hee accompted the onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his owne eſtate. But the Emperour on the other ſide beeing exceedingly offended with this reuolt of Octauio to the French, practiſed with the Pope to claime Parma as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right of the Church, and to excomunicate Octauio as the Church rebel, promiſing him if he would ſo doe, that hee would enter into theſe warres and beſiege Parma, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to the Church if it were recouered.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon the Pope reſpecting his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his credit or the goodneſſe of the cauſe: vtterly abandoned Octauio and ioyned with the Emperour in this warre. But the king hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued Octauio into his protection and that by the Popes owne perſwaſion, promiſed to defend him both againſt the Emperors ambition and violence, and likewiſe againſt the Popes trecherous incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, who as you haue heard being reuolted from Octauio, ioyned with the Emperour in this warre in hope to recouer Parma for the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the king fortefied Parma and manned it, and likewiſe Mirandula, the Earle whereof fearing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to be ſurpriſed by Gonzague, ioyned with the French, and receaued into the towne certaine French bands ſent thither out of Piemont by the marſhal Briſſac. Gonzague on the other ſide by the Emperours commaundement went and beſieged Parma but all in the Popes name, for neither would the Emperour ſeeme to attempt any thing againſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:9751:62"/>
the King, but onely to aide the Pope in a iuſt cauſe, neither would the King ſeeme to attempt any thing againſt the Emperour, but onely to ayde Octauio beeing vnder his protection in his iuſt cauſe.</p>
                  <p>But this diſſimulation betweene theſe two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces held not long, for as <hi>Monſieur d'Andelot</hi> paſſed through the Emperours dominions in Lombardie with certaine bandes of men, to put himſelfe into Parma by the Kings commandement, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they paſſed quietlie without harme doing as in their friendes country, yet was the ſaid <hi>d'An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delot</hi> ſtaied priſoner by the Imperialls and iuſtefied for a good przſe, wherevpon the King charged the Emperour with breach of the truce and beegan to make warre vpon him on all ſides.</p>
                  <p>A man may thinke the King was not well adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to enter into this warre for Octauios cauſe, in whom being the Emperours ſonne in law he could repoſe no aſſured truſt, and who hee mought aſſure himſelfe vpon the reſtitution of Placentia would alwaies be ready to giue him the ſlip, &amp; ſo in deede he did being reſtored therevnto in the yeare 1556. But you muſt know that the king vſed this matter but as a coulour to prouoke an open warre bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Emperour and him, as hee was ſure it would in the ende, and the which thing he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally deſired, both becauſe hee was yong and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally enclined to martiall affaires, and alſo becauſe hee hoped while the Emperour was buſied with the Princes of Allemaine, with whom the king had
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:9751:62"/>
good intelligence, to recouer the duchie of Milan, in the which as alſo in diuers other parts of Italie he had many good friends. But the warrs of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie had a ſpeedier end then hee expected, after the which the Emperour held him play in ſo many places, that hee had no leaſure to looke ouer the mountaines in a good many yeares after this, and ſped but euill when he toke that enterpriſe in hand as heereafter you ſhall heere. And ſo it appeereth that whatſoeuer man purpoſeth God diſpoſeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards thereof as it pleaſeth him. Gonzague as you haue heard beſiged Parma, &amp; the Pope on the other ſide, to diſtract the kings forces beſieged Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula.</p>
                  <p>But the King auowing the truce to bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, beecauſe of <hi>Monſieur d'Andelots</hi> impriſonment aboue mentioned, ſent to Briſſac new ſupplies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Piemont, commaunding him not onely to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour Parma and Mirandula, but alſo to endamage the Emperours dominions in thoſe partes by all the meanes he mought.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon the ſaide Briſſac wanne diuers townes in Piemont &amp; in the Marquiſate of Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrate from the Imperialls, and put the whole Duchie of Milan into ſo great feare that Gonzague was forced for the defence thereof to abandon the ſiege of Parma &amp; retire thether. The Pope alſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed no better beefore Mirandula, but loſt many of his men before the towne, and among the reſt his Nephew <hi>Giouanni Battiſta de Monte.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:9751:63"/>
Wherfore ſeing his hope fruſtrate for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recouerie of Parma and Mirandula, and being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with the charges of the warres, and farther perceauing a new tempeſt readie to ariſe againſt the Emperour from Duke Maurice, and other princes of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, with whom while the Emperour was buſied, himſelfe by the French mought be vtterly ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Wherevnto I alſo adde that the king had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie forbidden any cauſe whatſoeuer to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of his realme to Rome, which was no ſmall blow to the Popes purſe, and farther had vtterly refuſed to ſend any of the Clergie of his Realme to the counſell of Trent or to accept that as a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall counſell, and had alſo perſwaded the Swyſſers to doe the lyke, greatly to the derogation of his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie pontificall: for theſe reaſons I ſay the Pope ended the warres of Parma and Mirandula, and not onely forſoke the Emperour, but alſo deliuered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Earle of Mirandula all thoſe fortes that during the ſiege thereof had hene built at the Emperours charge, ſo that by the Popes treaſon the French held Mirandula made impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable by the Emperours purſe. The kings nauie alſo vpon the ſea toke diuers Flemiſh and Holan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh ſhippes of great price, and the Turke likewiſe about this time wanne Tripoly in Africk from the Emperour, which the ſayde Emperour toke very grieuouſly and attributed the loſſe thereof to the king by whoſe perſwaſion the Turke conuerted his forces thither as the Emperour ſayde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:9751:63"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>VVarres betweene the Emperour and the Princes of Germanie. Tbe king ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth into Germanie, hee carrieth away the duke of Lorraine, inuadeth Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg, Haynault and Picardie,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue heard before how the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Germanie were euell affected towards the Emperour for tirannizing ouer their Countrey, and eſpecially Duke MAVRICE beecauſe the Lantz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graue his father in law was ſtill held priſoner by the Emperour, for whoſe deliuerie duke MAVRICE had layde his honor to pawne, wherfore ſeing they could haue no reaſon at the Emperors hands, they purpoſed to obtaine it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, &amp; hauing made a firme league with the king they leuyed a mighty armie, and aſſaulted the Emperour vpon ſuch a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, <note place="margin">1552.</note> that he was forced for feare of his life to flye from Iuſburg through the mountaines in the night by torchlight with a ſmall company, where in his paſſage hee had almoſt broaken his neck. A ſtraunge chaunge of Fortune, that ſo mightie and glorious an Emperour, the lyke of whom Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had not ſeene in many hundered yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhould be thus purſewed and that by his owne ſubiect, yea and ſuch a ſubiect as himſelfe not long
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:9751:64"/>
before had highly aduanced. Notwithſtanding ſoone after by the mediatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the king of <hi>Romaines</hi> the Emperours brother, peace was concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Emperour and his Princes, and the Lantzgraue and the Duke of Saxonie were reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their libertie, notwithſtanding that the later of them would not depart from the Emperour, but folowed him in all theſe trobleſome broyles, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would not receaue his libertie by Duke Maurice his meanes.</p>
                  <p>The King on the other ſide during theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles betweene the Emperour and theſe Allemaine Princes, accordingly as was agreed betweene him and the ſayde Princes, entered into Germanie, with the title of Protector of the libertie thereof, and toke Metz in Lorraine an Imperiall towne, and likewiſe Thoul, Verdun, and Nancy, and carryed away the young Duke of Lorraine with him, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he marched as farr as Strauſbourg &amp; Hagenau neere to Spire, where the Ambaſſadors of the Princes of the Empire came to him and gaue him thankes for his readie ſuccour in the defence of the libertie of Germanie, and ſignified alſo vnto him that they beeing now reconciled to the Emperour ſhould haue no occaſion farther to craue his ayde. Wherevpon the king withdrew his forces out of Germanie, the rather becauſe hee was giuen to vnderſtand that Martin van Roſſem had entered and ſpoyled ſome part of Campaine, and that the queene of <hi>Hungarie</hi> had taken <hi>Astenay</hi>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:9751:64"/>
a ſmall towne vppon the Meuze belonging to the Duke of Lorraine. Wherefore the king entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Duchie of Luxembourg, and wanne diuers townes there, hee toke priſoner alſo there the Earle of Manſfelde and reſtored Bouillon to the houſe of <hi>La Marche.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Conſtable likewiſe by the kings commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement entered into Haynault and Picardie and made great ſpoyle there, which beeing done, the king becauſe of the foule wether diſmiſſed his army and in great triumph returned to Paris.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>The Emperour beſiegeth Metz. The Prince of Salerna reuolteth from the Emperour, and likewiſe the towne of Syena. The armie Imperiall inuadeth Picardie, Briſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſac in Piemont winneth Alba. Thero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna is razed by the Imperials.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Emperour hauing pacefied the Princes of Germanie, leuyed a mightie armie, purpoſing at one inſtant both to recouer Metz, and to inuade Fraunce. But the king ſent to the defence of the towne Francis duke of Guyſe accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo many noble men, and valyaunt ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, that the Emperour with great loſſe both of honor, men, munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; money was forced in the ende to abandon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiege, which he began in <hi>October</hi>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:9751:65"/>
a very vnſeaſonable time of the yeare, vppon his owne obſtinate will, and contrarie to the aduice of all the Captaines that were in his campe.</p>
                  <p>When the Emperour made his approaches to the towne, two ſkirmiſhes worthie of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance happened, one made by the French iſſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the towne vppon the Duke of Alua, in the which the ſayd Duke loſt 150. men with loſſe onely of 5. on the French part.</p>
                  <p>But to requite this ouerthrow you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that Albert Marques of Brandembourg, who had beene againſt the Emperour in the warres of Germanie aboue mentioned, being then in pay with the king, &amp; had euer ſithens thoſe warres en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, runne with his troupes all ouer <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, robbing, and raunſoming all thoſe that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came maſter of, eſpecially, <hi>Abbies,</hi> Nunries, Buſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rikes, and all whoſoeuer of the eccleſiaſticall ſtate? now ſeeing the warres open betweene the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the king, and meaning to recouer the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours fauour: came with his armie beeing to the number of 12000 towards the ſiege of Metz, and ſo houered vp and downe beetweene the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours campe and the places held by the French that hee put the King in hope that hee came to his ſeruice.</p>
                  <p>But the Duke d'Aumale diſcouering his practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with the Emperour, ſet vpon him with certaine troupes of horſemen being vnder his leading, but to his owne coſt, for the Marques ouerthrew him
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:9751:65"/>
and toke him priſoner &amp; receaued 50000. crownes for his ranſome, which the duche<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Valentinoys the kings Minion and mother in law to the ſayde Duke cauſed the king to pay.</p>
                  <p>After this the ſayde Marques ouerthrew alſo a great conuoy of victualls comming to the reliefe of the towne of Met<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and that beeing done reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe with all his Troupes into the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours campe.</p>
                  <p>Farther you ſhall vnderſtand that during this ſiege of Metz, the Prince of Salerne in the Realme of Naples, beecauſe of the extreame tirannie and crueltie that Don Piedro de Toledo vncle to the Duke of Alua vſed in the Countrey whereof the ſayde Prince could haue no redreſſe at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours hands turned French, as dyd alſo the towne of Siena hauing firſt razed the citadelle built by the Emperour to oppreſſe their libertie, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all the Spaniards out of their towne.</p>
                  <p>An other armie of the Emperours vnder the leading of <hi>Monſieur de Reux</hi> entered into <hi>Picardie,</hi> and burned many townes and vilages, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Caſtell of <hi>Foulenbray</hi> a place wherein the king toke great delight, they wanne alſo <hi>Heſdin</hi> both towne and Caſtell and many other places, notwithſtanding the nineteenth of December in this very yeare <hi>Monſieur de Vendoſme</hi> recouered <hi>Heſdin</hi> and afterward all the other townes, and on the other ſide the <hi>Marſhall</hi> of <hi>Briſſac</hi> in <hi>Piemom</hi> w<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n from the Emperour the towne of <hi>Alba.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:9751:66"/>
But to returne to the ſiege of Metz. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the Emperour vſed all warlike attempts, for the taking of the towne, and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually beat it with artilerie, that it is reported by ſome his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie to haue beene heard as farre as Strauſbourg, and by otherſome aboue 22. Duch miles from the towne: yet was the induſtrie of thoſe within the towne, and the miſerie of his ſouldiours without the towne ſuch, his camp being moſt grieuouſly afflicted with the plague, famine, bluddie flux, and cold, the ſiege continewing in the midſt of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame winter as before you haue heard: that hee was forced to leuie his ſiege &amp; returne into Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the ſecond day of Ianuarie 1553. after the Duch &amp; Italian accompt who begin the yeare the firſt of Ianuarie, but 1552. after the French who begin it not till Eaſter. At his departure to the ende hee mought returne with the more ſpeede, he caſt into the Riuer a great part of his artilerie, and munition for the warres, farther hee loſt in this ſiege 40000. men, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ignominie thereof ſo much afflicted him, that he forbare all communication with men, and ſoone after reſigned the Empire to his brother and his orher ſtates to his ſonne, and put himſelfe into an Abbie in Spaine where he ended his dayes.</p>
                  <p>Such miſfortunes Princes often fall into, when they are wedded to their owne wills and reiect all good aduiſe or rather when GOD is purpoſed to puniſh them, and to chaunge their good fortune into bad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:9751:66"/>
It is reported that the Emperours armie ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned ſo extreame miſerie in this ſiege, that one day as hee roade thorow his Campe, a poore ſouldier beeing miſerably afflicted with the blud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye fluxe cryed out thus to him as he paſſed by, <hi>Thou ſonne of a mad woman how much miſerie doe I and many a thouſand more endure heere through thy ambition and wilfull obſtinancie. If thou wert not tainted with thy mothers humor, thou wouldeſt neuer haue brought vs to this ſiege, at this time of the yeare,</hi> which words the Emperour hearing gaue no euell anſwere therevnto, but onely ſayde <hi>good words ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour this matter ſhall bee remedied ere long be,</hi> and with that gaue the poore ſoule money wherewith to comfort himſelfe, and ſoone after rayſed his ſiege, leauing a great number behinde him ſicke, whom the enemies of very pitie ſuccoured and relieued. But notwithſtanding the Emperours euell fortune here before Metz, his armie in Picardie vnder the leading of <hi>Monſieur de Reux</hi> beſieged <hi>Therouenne,</hi> in the which ſiege the ſayd <hi>de Reux</hi> dyed, after whoſe death <hi>Monſieur de Lalain</hi> continued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſiege, &amp; with a mine ouerthrew the fortifications, wherevpon <hi>Montmorency</hi> the Conſtables ſonne Gouernour of the towne, yeelded the place, and withall himſelfe and diuers other noble men of Fraunce priſoners.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:9751:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.<hi>The Imperialls raze Heſdin. The Duke of Arſcot is taken priſoner. The death of Edward the ſixt King of England, and of Duke Maurice. The king inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Emperour with three armies, the battaile of Renty.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Emperour becauſe of the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that was among his Captaines, made the Duke of Sauoye generall of his armie, who in Iulie recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo <hi>Heſdin</hi> from the French, in the which the duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> was taken priſoner, and razed the Caſtle, as the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials before had done the Caſtell of <hi>Therouenne,</hi> &amp; buylt a new <hi>Heſdin</hi> in a more conuenient place vppon the Riuer of <hi>Cauche,</hi> which they called <hi>Heſdinfiert.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From thence the Duke of Sauoy marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Dourlans</hi> and <hi>Amiens,</hi> where the Conſtable with part of the Kings armie, met with certaine of his troupes vpon the fifteenth of Auguſt, and hauing layde diuers ambuſhes to entrap them, charged them and ouerthrew them and toke pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner the Duke of <hi>Arſcot,</hi> who was led to <hi>Boys de Vincennes</hi> neere to <hi>Paris,</hi> whence hee eſcaped in the yeare 1556, wherevpon the Emperour ieaſted
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:9751:67"/>
of him ſaying, that he was taken like a begger and ſcaped away like a theefe.</p>
                  <p>Farther the king in perſon with a mightie armie entered into <hi>Artoys,</hi> and came before <hi>Cambray,</hi> where the Imperiall armie lay, in ſuch ſort that the battaile was looked for there, but it fell other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe out, wherevpon the king returned to Paris, leauing the Marſhall of Saint <hi>Andre</hi> to ſpoyle the Countrey.</p>
                  <p>In this yeare the ſixth of Iulie dyed Edward king of England a young Prince of rare expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to him ſucceeded Marie his ſiſter Coſin germaine to the Emperour, who about Saynt Iames tide the nezt yeare maryed with the Prince of Spaine the Emperours ſonne. And the ninth of Iulie was a cruell battaile fought in Germanie betwene Duke MAVRICE, and Albert Marques of Brandenbourg, in the which the ſayde Albert was vanquiſhed and Duke MAVRICE loſt his liſe.</p>
                  <p>You haue heard how the king returned to Paris leauing the Marſhall of Saint Andre behinde him <note place="margin">1554.</note> to ſpoyle the Countrey of Artoys. But the next ſommer the king leuied three armies, one vnder the leading of the Prince of <hi>Roche ſur Yonne</hi> was ſent into Artoys where it ſpoyled many townes &amp; villages. The Conſtable with an other armie entered into Haynault, and the Duke of Neuers, with a third into the countrey of Ardennes and Liege, where he burned and ſpoiled all the country before him. The Conſtable likewiſe in Haynault
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:9751:68"/>
burnt Cymay, a towne appertaining to the Duke of <hi>Arſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot, Trelon,</hi> and <hi>Glayon,</hi> and tooke Mariembourg through the cowardiſe of him that defended it, with the fame of the which victorie the king being inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, came in perſon into his army, and tooke Bouui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Brabant and burned it, and ſacked Dinand. But the Emperour leuied a mightie power to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter him vnder the leading of the Duke of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoy. Wherevpon the King returned againe into Haynault and deſtroyed Bins and Mariemount the Queene of Hungaries places of pleaſure, in reuenge of Folenbray in Picardie, which the Imperialls bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the yeare 1552. as before you haue heard, &amp; thus hauing burned and ſpoiled all Haynault, the King with his army entered into Artoys and beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Renty. But the Emperour with his whole force came to leauie the ſiege in ſuch ſort that a battaile was there fought betweene the king and him, in the which the ſucceſſe on both ſides was ſo equall that the victorie can iuſtlie be attributed to neither part, ſome call it but a halfe battaile. Notwithſtanding this was the battaile in the which it was firſt found by experience, that the rutters with their Piſtoles are not able to abide the force of the Launce, if they be roughly and reſolutely charged. The next day as the King was returning to the ſiege of the towne, he reccaued newes that his forces were ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in Italie, wherevpon he retired and returned to Montrueil and the Emperour likewiſe to Brux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:9751:68"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>The warres of Siena. Briſſacs ſucceſſe in Piemont. Pope Iulius dieth. Paule the fourth ſuccedeth. The French in Piemont take Vulpian. The Fight beetweene the French and Flemiſh Nauies before Douer. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour reſigneth the Empire and all his other eſtates.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ouerthrow the French receaued in Italie happened thus. You haue heard before how while the Emperour lay at the ſiege of Metz, the towne of Sienne in Italie reuolted from him, &amp; razed the Citadelle built by him, chaſed the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards out of the towne, and put themſelues into the protection of France. Wherewith he being not a little offended, after the ſaid ſiege was ended com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Viceroy of Naples to ſpoile all the country of Sienne, which he did accordinglie pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing alſo to beſige the towne, which <hi>Mouluc, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</hi> &amp; diuers others ſent therher by the king for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof, fortified againſt the Imperialls. The Viceroy becauſe of the reuoult that happened alſo at this very inſtaunt in the realme of Naples by meanes of the Prince of Salerna whereof wee haue ſpoken a word or two alſo in the ſaid ſiege of Metz, was forced to returne into the ſaid realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, leauing the charge of the Imperiall forces in the country of Siena to the Marques of Marignan, who being ayded by Coſmus Duke of Florence, and the Pope wenr and beſieged Siena.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:9751:69"/>
But vnderſtanding that <hi>Strozzi</hi> with great forces was ſent by the king into Italie, and that hee had alreadie inuaded the Duke of Florence his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, taken diuers places from him, and was gone to batter Ciuitelle; the ſayd Marques raiſed his ſiege from before Syena, and went with his whole power to ſuccour the Duke of Florence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon <hi>Strozzi</hi> leuied his ſiege held before Ciuitelle and marched to encounter the Marques and giue him battaile, in the which the ſayde <hi>Strozzi</hi> was ouerthrowen and put to flight and all his forces diſperſed. The Marques after this victorie retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſiege of Siena, &amp; neuer departed thence till he had reduced it to the Emperours obedience, by whoſe commaundement it was deliuered to the duke of Florence.</p>
                  <p>The ſayde ſiege endured till the twentieth of Aprill in the yeare 1555. But in December in the ſayde yeare 1554. Briſſac to repaire this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of <hi>Strozzi</hi> entered into Piemont, and toke diuers townes of great importaunce and fortefied them againſt the Imperialls</p>
                  <p>This yeare alſo 1554. the 23. of March after the French accompt who begin not the yeare till Eaſter, dyed Pope Iulius tertius, to whom ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Marcellus,</hi> who liued but a few dayes, and to him ſucceded Cardinall Caraffa being foure ſcore yeares of age by the name of Paule the fourth.</p>
                  <p>The French armie aboue mentioned vnder the <note place="margin">1555.</note> leading of <hi>Briſſac</hi> toke <hi>Caſſal,</hi> &amp; diuers other townes
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:9751:69"/>
in the Marquiſat of Montferrat, and went to beſiege <hi>Vulpian</hi> in Piemont, which the Duke of Alua with a mightie army came to relieue as alſo hee did. And hauing put victuals and munition ſufficient into the towne, he departed and beſieged Saint Iac.</p>
                  <p>But the towne was ſo notablie defended by the French (for the king had ſent thether great forces to ſuccour the place) that the Duke of Alua was forced to abandon the ſiege &amp; retire himſelfe, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie whervpon the French with their whole for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces returned to the ſiege of Vulpian, and toke it and razed both towne and caſtle, becauſe it maintained none but ſouldiours that robbed and ſpoiled all the country.</p>
                  <p>About this time alſo the French and Flemiſh Nauy met vpon the Sea, neere to Douer a hauen towne in England, where was a moſt bloddie fight betweene them, in the which the French being put to the worſe, fired their ſhips, thinking thereby to cauſe the flemings to vngraple from them, but the fire was ſo vehement that they had no powre to doe it, by meanes wherof both the Nauies were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and many ſhips on both ſides burnt.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding the French being entered into the flemiſh ſhips that remained, &amp; ſeeing the ſmall number of Flemings that were in them, tooke fiue of their ſhips, and led them away with them.</p>
                  <p>This yeare alſo vpon the fiue and twentith of October, the Emperour in great ſolempnitie in the great hall of Bruxelles, yelded vp all his eſtats and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:9751:70"/>
dominions patrimoniall to his ſonne king Phillip, and the Empire to the king of Romaines his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>A truce for fiue yeares betweene the King of Fraunce and Spaine. The Emperour ſaileth into Spaine, and putteth himſelfe into an Abbye where hee dieth.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the Emperour had reſigned all his eſtats to his ſonne King Phillip, <note place="margin">1556.</note> the ſaide King by the perſwaſion of the Queene of England his wife, and as ſome alſo writ by the Emperours owne perſwaſion, enclined to make peace with Fraunce, by meanes whereof both the Princes ſent their commiſſioners to meete &amp; treat therof, who not beeing able becauſe of the ſundry difficulties to conclude a finall peace, made not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a truce for fiue yeares, each part hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which they had taken in the former warrs. And in this yeare the Emperour with his two ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Elenor Queene of Fraunce, &amp; Marie Queene of Hungarie ſailed into Spaine, and put himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Abby, wher he remained till his death, which happened the one and twentith of September in the yeare 1558. One notable thing is to bee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:9751:70"/>
of this noble Emperour, wherby we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue how vaine a thing the glory of this world is. While the Emperour ſtayed at Vluſhing for winde to carie him his laſt iourney into Spaine, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on a time with <hi>Seldius</hi> his brother Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nands Ambaſſador till the deepe of the night, and when <hi>Seldius</hi> ſhould depart, the Emperour calling for ſome of his ſeruants, and no bodie anſwering him, for thoſe that attended vpon him were ſome gone to their lodgings and all the reſt a ſleepe: the Emperour tooke vp the candle himſelfe, and went before <hi>Seldius</hi> to light him downe the ſtaires, and ſo did notwithſtanding all the reſiſtance that <hi>Seldius</hi> could make.</p>
                  <p>And whan he was come to the ſtaires foote, hee ſaid thus vnto him. <hi>Seldius</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber this of Charles the Emperour when he ſhalbe dead and gone that him whom thou haſt knowen in thy time enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſo many mightie armies and gardes of ſouldiers, thou haſt alſo ſeene alone, abandoned, &amp; forſaken yea euen of his owne domeſticall ſeruants, and that hee whom thou haſt ſerued ſo manye yeares hath alſo ſerued thee and borne the candle downe before thee, I acknowledge this chaunge of fortune to proceede from the mightie hand of God, which I will by no meanes goe about to withſtand.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:9751:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. <hi>The truce for fiue yeares is broken by the Popes practiſe. The Duke of Alua inuadeth the Church Dominions. The Duke of Guyſe entereth into Italie, and the King inuadeth the King of Spayne in diuers other places. The Queene of England proclaymeth warre againſt the French.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou haue heard how a truce for fiue yeares was concluded betweene the <note place="margin">1557.</note> Kings of Fraunce and Spaine, but it was broken before the expiration of one yeare, vpon this occaſion which you ſhall now heare. The Pope being an enemie to the Spaniard, gaue forth whether falſly or true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is vncertaine, that the Colonneſi who alwayes haue beene and yet are Imperiall, made ſecret aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies againſt him in Rome, for the which cauſe ſome of them hee empriſoned, ſome hee baniſhed, and ſeazed all their lands and goods into his owne hands. The Imperials ſay that this was but a quarell picked to them by the Pope, becauſe hee had ſecret intelligence with the king of Fraunce, &amp; perſwaded him to attempt the recouerie of the Realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as well therby to abate the Spaniards greatnes in Italie, who held <hi>Naples, Milan,</hi> &amp; <hi>Siena,</hi> &amp; diſpoſed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:9751:71"/>
of the ſtats of Genoua &amp; Florence as of his owne: as alſo hoping if the French had good ſucceſſe in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie, that ſome part of the bootie would fall to his ſhare, which hee was the more deſirous of, becauſe he was a Neapolitaine borne himſelfe. But howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it were, the <hi>Colonneſi</hi> being thus iniuried com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to king Philip and deſired his ſuccour, who ſent the Duke Alua to their ayde, yet offering the Pope any reaſonable conditions of peace, which he vtterly refuſed, and ſent to the king and the duke of Ferrara being his confederats for ſuccours, but before they could arriue, the duke of Alua inuaded the Church dominions, and toke <hi>Ostia</hi> &amp; <hi>Paleſtrina</hi> and much diſtreſſed <hi>Rome.</hi> But the King with all ſpeede ſent the Duke of Guyſe with a mightie ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie into Italie, who entering into <hi>Lombardie</hi> tooke <hi>Valentia</hi> in the duchie of Milan &amp; put a gariſon into it, on an other ſide alſo the French inuaded Artoys and ſpoyled all the Countrey, they beſieged <hi>Douay</hi> but could not take it. Notwithſtanding <hi>Lens</hi> they toke and burned it. Farther the kings forces in Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont tooke <hi>Valfiniere</hi> and <hi>Cairas,</hi> and thus the fiue yeares truce concluded the yeare before helde not one yeare, great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie is betwene the French and Spaniſh, which of the two Princes firſt brake the truce. The French ſay the Spaniard firſt brake it by inuading the Pope, whom the king as an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſonne to the Church was bound to defend.</p>
                  <p>But the anſwere herevnto is eaſie, for beſides that the inuading of the Pope being an indifferent
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:9751:72"/>
friend to both the Princes could not bee a breach of the truce towards the French king: it is alſo moſt certaine that the firſt iniurie proceded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Pope,</hi> towards the king of Spaines friends and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federats, and therefore the French were not to ayde him in an euell cauſe. But admit the ayding of the Pope were no breach of the truce: yet the King ought not to haue proceded farther then to ſend the <hi>Pope</hi> ayde, but hee inuaded king Philip before he tooke weapon in hand, in Milan, in Piemont, in Artoys, and in Flaunders, which could not bee other then a flatte breach of the truce. But to retourne to the warres of Italie. The Duke of Guyſe by the Popes perſwaſion, and vppon promiſe of ayde from him, was paſſing with his armie towards the realme of Naples with purpoſe to inuade it. But ſeeing the Duke of Alua to make head againſt him, and being alſo diſapoynted of the ayde promiſed him by the Pope, he was forced to retire with his armie, being in very pore eſtate and curſing the Pope and all his trecheries. While theſe matters thus paſſed in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the Queene of England by hir huſbands per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion entered into an vnneceſſarie warre with Fraunce, for ſhe ſhould haue done much better to haue continued as ſhee began a mediater for peace th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n vpon no occaſion to become the French kings enemie, but ſhee ſped accordingly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:9751:72"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cha.</hi> 10. <hi>The King of Spaine taketh Saint Quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. The battaile of Saint Laurens in the which the Conſtable is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen and taken priſoner. The duke of Guyſe is reuoqued out of Italie. The Pope maketh peace with the king of Spaine. The French take Calais. The marriage of the Daulphin. The French take Theonuille.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BVt to proceede the king of Spaine, ſeeing him ſelfe thus inuaded vpon a ſodayne, leuyed a mightie armie of Duch Flemiſh and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and went and beſieged Saint Quentin a ſtronge towne in Vermandoys, for the defence whereof the Admirall of Fraunce Gaſper <hi>Chaſtillon,</hi> with diuers bandes of men put himſelfe into the towne. But his brother <hi>d'Andelot</hi> iſſewing out of Perona with 15. enſeignes of footmen, purpoſing to doe the like, was defeated. Notwithſtanding the king tendering greatly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaftie of the towne, ſent the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtable</hi> to ſuccour it with an armie of 16000. foot, and 4000. horſe, who vpon Saint Laurence day ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry earely in the morning, by certaine boates which he had brought with him vpon cartes, put <hi>Mon ſieur d'Andelot</hi> by the riuer with certaine bands of foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into the towne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="136" facs="tcp:9751:73"/>
But King Phillips army as the ſaid Conſtable reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, charged him, brake him, defeated his forces, ſlew 2500 of his men with the loſſe onely of 50. on their part, and tooke him priſoner with two of his ſonnes, and likewiſe the Dukes of Montpenſier and Longueuille, the Marſhall of Saint Andre, the Rheingraue, and diuers other great perſonages.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon the King preſentlie reuoqued the Duke of Guiſe with his forces out of Italy, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Duke of Neuers to leauy a new army.</p>
                  <p>In the meane time King Phillip tooke Saint Quentin by aſſault, and tooke priſoners therin the Admirall, and <hi>d'Andelot</hi> his brother, but <hi>d'Andelot</hi> ſoone after eſcaped away. The King of Spaine wan alſo Catelet and Han and diuers other places. The Duke of Alua on the other ſide in Italie tooke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places from the Pope, who in the end ſeeing the Dukes forces ſo great that he came without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance euen to Rome gates, and that the Duke of Guiſe in verie poore eſtate was reuoqued home in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce: made peace at Caui with King Philip (contraty to his promiſe made to the French King) and obtayned better conditions of him than he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and among the reſt of the conditions this was one that the Duke of Guiſe ſhould returne home in ſafetie, and he &amp; his armie bee well intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whereſoeuer they paſſed through king Philips dominions, which was all the recompence the French receaued at the Popes handes, for the great
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:9751:73"/>
loſſes they had receaued in Italie by his meanes, ſuch commonly is the ende of all vnneceſſarie warres.</p>
                  <p>The King being much grieued with theſe his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde loſſes, and ſuppoſing his honour to be ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if he atchieued not ſome enterpriſe that might counteruaile theſe his miſfortunes, ſo ſoone as the Duke of Guiſe and Strozzi were returned with his forces out of Italie by ſea, and <hi>Monſieur d'Aumalle</hi> by land, ioyned to them a great army of Swiſſers and Almaines who vnder the leading of the ſaid Duke of Guiſe were ſent to beſiege Calais in the verie middeſt of winter.</p>
                  <p>Strozzi not long before the comming of the army thether, had beene brought in diſguiſed appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raile into the towne by a French man an inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant thereof, and had veiwed all the fortiſications both within the towne and without, and the gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within it for the defence thereof, which was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weake, and to ſay the truth the ſaid Strozzi was the onely author of this enterpriſe</p>
                  <p>They began the ſiege the firſt day of Ianuarie, and tooke the towne the morrow after twelfth day, and ſoone after alſo Hams and Guyſnes, and all that the Engliſh helde on that ſide the ſea.</p>
                  <p>In Aprill following Frauncis the Daulphin maryed Marie daughter and heire of Iames the fift King of Scotland, &amp; in Iune following the French beſiged Theonuille, held for an impregnable towne in the Dutchie of Luxembourg. Yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:9751:74"/>
they tooke it, but in that ſiege was Peter Stroz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zi ſlaine to the Kings great griefe, for he had beene a moſt valiant and expert Captaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> II. <hi>The French inuade Flaunders and ſacke Dunkerke, they are ouerthrowen in their retrait to Calais. The Engliſh Nauy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Conquet. Peace betweene the Kings of Spaine and Fraunce and Elizabeth Queene of England. Bourg and other Councellours of the law are ſent to the Baſtile. The Kings daughter is maried to the King of Spaine. The King is ſlaine at the iuſts.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt the King ſuppoſing this reuenge of his loſſes not to be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as yet, determined to attempt farther. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in the beginning of Iulie he ſent <hi>Monſieur de Termes</hi> to inuade Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who tooke Dunkerke and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it. But the Earle of Egmont leuying an army of 12000. foote and 3000 horſe, met with the French as they retired towards Calais vpon the ſandes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Dunkerke and Grauelin, where he charged them, and by the helpe of the Engliſh Nauy, which by chaunce ſailed at that time cloſe by the ſhoare, and diſcharged their great ſhot into the middeſt of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:9751:74"/>
the French troups, they were deſeated and Termes himſelfe taken priſoner, to the great aſtoniſhment of all Fraunce, which in ſower yeares ſpace had receaued three great ouerthrowes, the firſt in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, the ſecond at Saint Quentin, and the third this heere mentioned.</p>
                  <p>And thus the King not beeing contented with a reaſonable reuenge, but ſeeking to recouer all his honour, loſt euen that which hee had in part recouered before, and put both himſelfe and his Realme into greater daungers than euer heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore they had beene in.</p>
                  <p>Termes had left behinde him three enſeignes of footemen to ſpoile and fier Dunkerke, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the middeſt of their blouddie execution, were all ſurprized by the Burgundians and cut in peeces. The Duke of Guiſe hearing of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow retired into Picardie, and held himſelfe in places of ſafetie.</p>
                  <p>After this victorie the Engliſh Nauy conſiſting of 100. ſaile of ſhips and 10000. men, and 20. great hulks ioyned with them, inuaded Bretaine and toke Conquet, but partlie by the force of the countrey that came downe vpon them, &amp; partlie by tempeſt, they were forced to returne home with ſpeed. King Phillip being encouraged by this his good ſucceſſe and many victories, leuied a mightie army, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped neere to Dourlans in Picardie beeing a French towne, his whole force was 30000. foote, &amp; 15000. horſe, all his ſouldiours being well paied.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:9751:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The king on the other ſide neere to Amiens, leuyed a great armie, but ſeemed not willing to hazerd an other battayle, conſidering the loſſes hee had alreadie receaued. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the ende both the Princes to auoyde the effuſion of Chriſtian blood enclined their mindes to peace.</p>
                  <p>The two and twentith of Ianuarie Charles Duke of LORRAINE maryed the Ladie Claude the kings younger Daughter, and the Februarie after, peace was treated of at Cambreſis bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Kings and ELIZABETH Queene of England latelie ſucceded to the Crowne of that Realme by the death of hir Siſter MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIE, who dyed the ſeauententh of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1558.</p>
                  <p>The Commiſſioners agreede reaſonably well about euerie thing ſaue CALAIS, which King Philip would haue in any caſe reſtored to the Engliſh againe, and the French would by noe meanes part with, which matter was ſo whotlie debated betweene them, that all the treatie had aſſuredlie broaken of, if newes had not beene brought from the Queene of England, that ſhee was contented to accept of the peace, with theſe conditions, that at eyght yeares ende Calais ſhould bee reſtored to hir agayne or fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiftie thouſand crownes in lieu thereof, for aſſuraunce whereof ſhee ſhould haue delyuered
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:9751:75"/>
vnto hir foure hoſtages of the nobilytie of Fraune ſuch as ſhee would demaund.</p>
                  <p>This article beeing agreed vpon peace was concluded beetweene theſe Princes the third of Aprill, and ſolemply proclaimed with great ioye: <note place="margin">1559.</note> And King Philip maryed ELIZABETH the Kings eldeſt Daughter promiſed beefore to CHARLES Prince of Spayne King Philips ſonne, and the Duke of SAVOY Philibert maryed MARGARET the Kings ſiſter.</p>
                  <p>Thus the king hauing concluded peace to his great comfort with all his enemies, and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauthed his Daughter to the king of Spayne, by meanes of the which allyaunce hee aſſured him ſelfe of an euerlaſting amitie with that Prince: beganne to embrew his handes in the bloud of the LVTHERANS, and committed BOVRG and foure other Iudges of the Law to MONTGOMERIE Captaine of his Guarde, who ſent them priſoners to the Baſtile, where they were layde in yrons.</p>
                  <p>The only cauſe of their empriſonment was, for that they had delyuered out of priſon certayne Lutherans, and had forborne to publiſh the kings bloudy edicts till a generall or a nationall councell ſhould take order in ſo wayghtie a cauſe.</p>
                  <p>This beeing done, the king in great triumph departed to his Daughters mariage, who was
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:9751:76"/>
maryed to king Philip by his Deputie the Duke of Alua, who repreſented the king his Maſters perſon in this caſe: which beeing accompliſhed the king gaue himſelfe to ſports and paſtimes, and the eight and twenteth of Iune entered into the Liſts to iuſt, and continewed ſo long therein, and ranne ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny courſes three dayes together, that with exceſſiue trauayle his whole body was become ſtiffe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon diuers of the nobilitie and eſpecially the Queene his wyfe beſought him to runne no more, the rather becauſe that night the Queene had drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that ſhee ſaw him wounded to death, &amp; diuers other prognoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his death are alſo written which I ouerpaſſe. But he refuſing all perſwaſions, &amp; deſpiſing his wiues dreame, &amp; all the other prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications, entered againe into the liſtes, &amp; ranne diuers courſes excellently well, for he was a perfect man at armes. At the laſt he called foorth Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomerie, the ſelfe ſame that had caryed BOVRG and the other foure Councellours to priſon, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you haue heard. Montgomerie had runne diuers courſes the day before, &amp; had ſayled in them all, for the which cauſe hee was loath to come forth. But being conſtrained by the king, in the ende foorth he came being reſerued by God to giue one ſound blow at the laſt, to counteruaile all his fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings before: For as the king and hee met together with great violence a ſplenter of Montgomeries ſtaffe which brake all to ſheuers, ſtrake the kings
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:9751:76"/>
head-peece full vpon the viſard, which being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buckled either through negligence, or becauſe the king would haue it ſo, meaning to make this his laſt courſe, flew vp, in ſuch ſort that one of the ſple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſtrake the king full in the right eye and entered into his very braine, which put this poore Prince to extreame paine. Vpon the ninth of Iulie he cauſed the mariage of his ſiſter &amp; the duke of Sauoy to bee accompliſhed without any pomp, which ſhould not haue bene ſolempniſated till eight dayes after, and the next day he dyed of the ſayde hurt. The wound ſoone made an ende of his owne life, but his realme hath bled of that wound euer ſince, &amp; the blood is hardly ſtenched as yet. This king liued one &amp; forty yeares, and reigned twelue yeares and 3. moneths, and tenne dayes.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I continued as compendiouſly as I could, the Hiſtorie of Fraunce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth till the death of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, namely til the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their owne ciuill broyles and diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which becauſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine nothing but murthers, maſſacers, trecheries, treaſons, and no orderly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplined warres, are nothing pleaſaunt for mee to write, nor I thinke acceptable to any man to reade, &amp; much leſſe fit to be annexed to the martiall actes of thoſe Princes, whom I haue here before in this Hiſtorie treated of. Notwithſtanding if any man ſhall take pleaſure in writing them, I had rather hee handeled ſuch a bucherly argument then my ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:9751:77"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. <hi>The concluſion of the Hiſtorie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow to conclude this Hiſtorie, can we haue any more notable examples than theſe heere aboue mentioned to proue that mans cogitations are vaine, and all his thoughts wicked, for if you conſider how all theſe Princes toſſed and turmoiled themſelues with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall warres, what infinit treaſures they conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, what ſlaughters they made of their ſubiects, what ſacking and burning of townes, defiling of yong Maidens and Virgins, murthering of women and Children, with all ſuch like miſchiefes as be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant to the warrs, and that is worſt of all, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne ſoules with manie promiſes and oathes which they neuer ment to performe when they ſware them, neither performed at all when they had ſworne them.</p>
                  <p>And if we farther conſider how little they haue effected and brought to paſſe of their owne deſires by all theſe their bloddy Martiall actions, with the which they troubled the world by the ſpace of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares: we cannot but confeſſe and ſay with the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Hee that dwelleth in the Heauen ſhall laugh, the Lord ſhall haue them in deriſion.</hi> For firſt of all conſider well the example of Lodouic Sforce ſurnamed the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:9751:77"/>
More Duke of Milan, hee poiſoned his nephew to obtaine therby the ſaid Duchie, and ſet all Italie on fier by calling in the French to eſtabliſh him therin, but himſelfe was within 5. yeares after taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner by the French, and put into a dongeon wher he miſerablie ended his life, his eldeſt ſonne Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian being reſtored to the ſaid Duchie of Milan by meanes of the Swiſſers, the Pope, and the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, was within three yeares after likewiſe taken priſoner by the French, and in Fraunce ended his daies.</p>
                  <p>Afterward his other ſonne Francis was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the ſaid Dutchie by the Emperour Charles, but with ſuch ſlauiſh conditions that he rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the name of a noble ſlaue than an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, and in the end died of poiſon as it was thought, and was the laſt of this wicked race of Sforces, &amp; after his death the Emperour ſeazed all the Duchie of Milan into his owne hands whoſe race holdeth it yet, and ſhall doe ſo long as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God: And all theſe miſeries fell vpon the ſaid Lodouic and his ſonnes within the ſpace of 34. yeares.</p>
                  <p>Now way likewiſe the example of Pope Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander the ſixt, and Valentinus Borgia his ſonne.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid Valentine in his fathers life time obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo many conqueſts in Italie, ſome by armes, ſome by crueltie, ſome by treaſon and trecheries, ſome by periurie, and by all other wicked meanes that may be imagined, that all Italie ſtoode in feare
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:9751:78"/>
of him, and he was growen to ſuch a pride in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee gaue <hi>Aut Caeſar aut nullus</hi> for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe.</p>
                  <p>The Father poiſoned himſelfe with the ſame wine that he had prepared for the poiſoning of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cardinalls his enemies, and ſo fell himſelfe into the pit which he had digged for others, and the ſon after his fathers death was ſpoiled by Pope Iulius of all that he had conquered in Italie, and the King of Fraunce toke from him all his eſtates that he held in Fraunce.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore he fled to Conſalue vnder his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct, and remained with him a while at Naples in great kindnes in outward apparance.</p>
                  <p>But ſoone after by King Ferdinands comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, hee was ſent priſoner into Spaine by the ſaid Conſalue, who alſo tooke from him, the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct that he had giuen him.</p>
                  <p>In Spaine he was empriſoned in the Rocque of <hi>Medina del Campo,</hi> from whence by cunning he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped, and went into Nauarre, where hee liued a while in very baſe and miſerable eſtate, and in the end was there ſlaine.</p>
                  <p>The Venetians likewiſe for hatred they bare againſt Lodouic Duke of Milan aboue mencioned, called Lewis the twelfth into Italie to conquer the ſaid Duchie, and had for their part of the bootie the countrey of Guiradadda deliuered vnto them by the King.</p>
                  <p>But ſoone after the ſame king toke it from them
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:9751:78"/>
againe, &amp; became their deadly enemie, ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their charges employed in thoſe warres and diuers other ſince: yet hould they not at this day one foote of ground in Lombardie more then they did before thoſe warres began, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of Italie leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Againe fower kings of Fraunce ſucceſſiuely, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly CHARLES the eight, LEVVIS the twelfth, FRANCIS the firſt, &amp; HENRY the ſecond, by the ſpace of three ſcore yeares and better, made conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall warres in Italie, with infinit expences of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, toyle of themſelues, and the death not of ſo few as a hundered thouſand of their ſubiects, for the duchie of Milan &amp; the realme of Naples, and what haue they gotten in recompence therof, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this that they hould not at this day one foote of Land in neither of both thoſe countreys.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe Charles the Emperour who was ſo am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious a Prince that hee thought to haue ſwalow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp both Fraunce and Germanie, was chaced out of both thoſe countries with great ignominie, and was neuer able to hould no not one pore towne in either of both thoſe realmes, &amp; in the end through moodineſſe of his euell ſucceſſe, gaue a deffiance to all the world, and dyed in an Abby among a companie of Monkes.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly king Henry the eight who was ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Prince, and obtained ſo many conqueſts in Fraunce both in his youth and in his age, what hath he leſt to his poſteritie in that Countrey, for
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:9751:79"/>
his infinite charges employed in thoſe warres? not one towne, no nor one foote of French land. Theſe examples I thinke may ſuffice to teach Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to bee wiſe, and not to attempt ambitiouſlie vnneceſſarie warrs, ſeeing the ſequell that enſeweth therof, but to liue peaceably at home, to entertaine the good will of their neighbours by all the good meanes they may, to ſe iuſtice done among their ſubiects which is their principall charge, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to ground all their actions vpon God, who is the guyder of all their enterpriſes, and the giuer of all good ſucceſſe. Happie is the Prince that thus gouerneth his ſubiects and happie are the ſubiects that liue vnder ſuch a Prince.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9751:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
